<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox cleri, or, The sense of the clergy concerning the making of alterations in the established liturgy with remarks on the discourse concerning the Ecclesiastical Commission and several letters for alterations : to which is added an historical account of the whole proceedings of the present convocation.</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2986</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13659370</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13659370</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 793:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox cleri, or, The sense of the clergy concerning the making of alterations in the established liturgy with remarks on the discourse concerning the Ecclesiastical Commission and several letters for alterations : to which is added an historical account of the whole proceedings of the present convocation.</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by R. Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Thomas Long.  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed and entered according to order."</note>
                  <note>"An historical account of the present convocation": p. 57-72.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Ecclesiastical Commission (1686)</term>
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101060:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VOX CLERI: OR, THE <hi>Senſe of the Clergy,</hi> Concerning the Making of ALTERATIONS IN THE <hi>ESTABLISHED LIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGY:</hi> WITH REMARKS on the Diſcourſe concerning the Eccleſiaſtical COMMISSION, and ſeveral Letters for ALTERATIONS. To which is Added, An Hiſtorical ACCOUNT OF THE Whole PROCEEDINGS OF THE Preſent Convocation.</p>
            <q>
               <p>My Son, fear thou the LORD, and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to Change,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. xxiv. xxi.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ipſa mutatio conſuetudinis etiam quae adjuvat utilitate novitate perturbat,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. ad Januarium Epiſt.</hi> 118. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed, and Entred according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>R. Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-hall.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:101060:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101060:2"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR'S PROTESTATION.</head>
            <p>TO cure the Prejudices with which too many are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prepoſſeſſed, and to prevent the growth and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous effects, which they may produce; I have thought it neceſſary for the ſecurity of my ſelf, and Brethren, to declare what our Perſwaſions are, as to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government both in Church and State. And firſt we have by our Oaths promiſed to bear Faith and true Allegiance to the King and Queens Majeſties. And the whole Clergy have renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Allegiance to their Majeſties, and their adherence to the Church as Eſtabliſhed, in their late Addreſs of Thanks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Whereby we doubt not but the Intereſt of the Proteſtant Religion in all other Proteſtant Churches</hi> (which is dear to us) <hi>will be better ſecured,</hi> &amp;c. So that whoever do repreſent them as enemies, either to the Church or State, or any Proteſtant Churches, do falſly and maliciouſly reproach them, or interpret that to be their ſin, which is their bounden duty, and care; and if theſe be our faults, I hope there is no ſort of people, who joyn with us in living, in obedience to the Laws of the Land, and in the Communion of the Church, will entertain thoſe Prejudices and hard thoughts of us, which ſome that are enemies to both, have from the Preſs, and from their Pulpits, ſcandalouſly ſuggeſted againſt us, to draw an Odium on the Conſultations of the whole Clergy in Convocation, and to
<pb facs="tcp:101060:3"/>incenſe the people againſt them, as enemies to peace and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, I only crave this kindneſs from thoſe that are influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced with theſe reports; <hi>1.</hi> To conſider, what our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries report of us: And <hi>2ly,</hi> what may be the reaſon of ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. The Author of the ſecond Letter (reflected on in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe) relating to the Convocation, hath theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions concerning ſuch as are not for Alterations, <hi>Pag. 6. I expect no leſs than that they become abhorred of the whole Nation, and as the common enemies of its peace be treated accordingly in every Pariſh where we live among them.</hi> P. <hi>5. That we have maintained Trifles with unreaſonable Rigor. And</hi> P. <hi>6. we have already loſt our reputation with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by inſiſting too rigorouſly on thoſe things.</hi> P. <hi>9. That there is an obligation upon us of coming to a change not to be reſiſted without guilt.</hi> P. <hi>20. That we are a baſe and falſe ſort of men that can promiſe in adverſity, and forget all when that is over.</hi> P. <hi>22. That we ſhall loſe the people of the Land, and give our Adverſaries advantage over us to our utter ruin.</hi> P. <hi>15. That the People are overthrown by Excommunications for a penny or two-penny cauſe. That we ſhall totally extinguiſh all Convocations for the future, and therefore he deſires them to conſider, whether the Church of</hi> England <hi>is now met together only to be</hi> Felo's de ſe, <hi>and</hi> (not to mention all his vile inſinuations) <hi>that in</hi> P. <hi>25. contains as much ſpite and venom as he could hold without breaking, ſuch</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as are moſt perverſely bent againſt reaſon and conſcience to do all the wickedneſs they can to gratifie a peeviſh humour.</hi> With <hi>theſe things</hi> he aſperſeth the whole Clergy in general, cloathing them as the Perſecutors of old did the Chriſtians, in Bears and Lions Skins, and ſo expoſed them to be devoured by ſuch creatures. But this Author comes to Particulars. And <hi>P. 25.</hi> ſays of the ſuſpended Biſhops (whom he acknowledgeth (as their greateſt enemies muſt) <hi>that they are excellent men)</hi> yet ſays, <hi>if they ſhould not conſent to Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, The reſentment of the State will be heavy on them
<pb facs="tcp:101060:3"/>as enemies to them and us, ſo as they will be immediately cruſh'd and fall to nothing.</hi> And more particularly he thus reflects on our worthy <hi>Prolocutor,</hi> as a man worthy of the death of the greateſt Criminal. For thus he ſaith of him, <hi>We have no reaſon to thank him for his Speech, or his Motto, the laſt of which I ſuppoſe pleaſed him beſt, becauſe it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a double ſtab with it, the one againſt the Church, the other againſt his greateſt Benefactor to promote him in it,</hi> Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum?</p>
            <p>But <hi>2ly,</hi> What is the cauſe of all this bitter zeal and inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate malice, it is only becauſe he fancieth they will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſuch Alterations as ſhall be propoſed to them; but firſt it may well be ſuppoſed, that neither he nor they do yet know what Alterations will be, for none have been as yet propoſed to them, and therefore to hang and draw before any crime be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged againſt them, is a moſt barbarous practice, eſpecially for one that is of the ſame Communion with them, and upon thoſe whom he acknowledgeth to be ſuch excellent men his Fathers and his Brethren. But thus did his Predeceſſors heretofore deſtroy the Church by ſuch malicious inſinuations from groundleſs fears and jealouſies, as the Jews did Crucifie our Saviour. <hi>Venient Romani,</hi> They will bring in Popery. But when the Church hath defeated that Engine, and made it wholly uſeleſs by root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the very foundations of Popery, ſuch men muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to other inventions. And the noiſe of Perſecution is rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt them, that they have been and would be again, if they had power, as great Perſecutors as the Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors were; but this clamor the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> with ſome others have ſilenced, proving undeniably that the Church of <hi>England</hi> had neither the temper nor the power to be of a Perſecuting ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And now the Cry is, That ſhe is of a peeviſh and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate humour, that againſt Reaſon and Conſcience hinders peace and reconciliation, and in ſum ſaith our Author, <hi>That ſhe is afraid of loſing her Church power and Church-promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:101060:4"/>though all the Nation knows with what general unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Chriſtian reſolution, the Clergy hazarded all their Promotions, by refuſing to publiſh the late Kings Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience, and ſuſpending the Penal Laws, which now their enemies plead for, in compliance with the preſent jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Affairs, and is as evident as any matter of fact can be; and little leſs evident is it, who they are that gape for the Preferments, which other men have ſignally deſerved, and are legally poſſeſſed of; if this be not enough wholly to cure the prejudices which have been inſinuated into the Minds of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous and inconſiderate Men; yet I hope that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, if duly conſidered, may prevent the prejudicate Opinions of ſuch as have any ſober Principles, or ſerious Thoughts, leaſt unawares they be tempted <hi>to curſe thoſe that bleſs them in the Name of the Lord, and to bleſs thoſe that curſe their Father and Mother;</hi> in that heretofore moſt abuſed Scripture, <hi>Judges 5.23. Curſe ye Meroz; curſe ye bitterly the inhabitants thereof, becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty: And bleſſed above Women ſhall they be that put their hands to the nail, and their right-hands to the workman's hammer, to ſmite off the head of</hi> Siſera, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the carved works of our Temples with Axes and Hammers.</hi> We are told <hi>that we have many Enemies,</hi> and ſo we ever had, and are like to have, as all may ſee, that read what comes from the Preſs, and what is preached from the Pulpit by Men of our own Communion: witneſs what was lately preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in ſeveral Congregations; <hi>That we are raiſing within our own mind, and in the minds of the people, over whom we have any influence, all the ſowerneſs and peeviſhneſs that is poſſible; That the things propoſed</hi> (when yet there is nothing propoſed) <hi>are of themſelves ſo deſirable, though there ſhould be no Diſſenter gained by them, and ſuch as will tend to the making all the parts of our Offices both more unexceptionable, and more edifying; and if we let ſlip the preſent advantages that we have, what is to be ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:101060:4"/>upon it? but that this is of the Lord, who by it is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us for our other Sins; for our remiſneſs in our Duties; for our neglect of our Paſtoral Care; for our ſlackning that ſtrictneſs of Life which becomes our Profeſſion; for our indulging our ſelves too much in Senſuality and Lazineſs; and he thanks God for the Liberty, that the Service of God is ſecured to all Men; of following the Dictates of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in the Service of God; and that we are freed from all the Remnants of the worſt part of Popery; that we had too long retained, I mean,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Spirit of Perſecution.</hi> Though the ſame perſon had vindicated the Church from ſuch a Spirit in ſeveral other Tracts; I ſhall only add, to make this Apology compleat, what <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Agrippa,</hi> Acts <hi>25.23. It ſeems to me unreaſonable to ſend a Priſoner, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to ſignifie the Crimes laid againſt him.</hi> And certainly, as yet, there are no Crimes laid againſt us of the Country, or you that are of the Convocation; for it cannot be a Crime in them that are Men of good Reputation, and honeſt Converſations, not to do that which is both againſt the Law of the Land, and againſt the Dictates of their own Conſciences: It is not a Crime for a Man not to do what none as yet hath required of him to do; It is not a Crime for a Man to do that which he is well perſwaded will be but loſt labour when it is done; and yet for theſe things we are defamed, accuſed, and condemned, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as ſo many Offenders to be executed at the will of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Were it ſo, that the Queſtion had been propoſed, whether we would admit of Alterations, or not; yet all Law and Equity gives Malefactors the priviledge of making a defence, eſpecially when their Reputation, their Livelihoods, and even their Lives are concern'd: An accuſed perſon ought to have his Enemy face to face; and hear his Inditement, and plead guilty or not guilty; but none of theſe things have yet been permitted to us: And if it be crime enough to be accuſed, no mortal Man hath his Innocency ſecured. Theſe are, I hope, competent Reaſons for this preſent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, it being a thing natural for a Man
<pb facs="tcp:101060:5"/>to defend himſelf, there being no living Creature ſo void of Senſe, as not to avoid another that attempts to deſtroy him; and every Worm will turn upon him that would tread on it: And if an innocent perſon chance to injure another that injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aſſaults him, he is alway held guiltleſs, as having done it <hi>Se defendendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, Sir, is what the irregular and groundleſs Proceedings of ſome Diſſenters have exacted from us, to mollifie, if it be poſſible, the Temper of the People, as well as to abate the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Calumnies of our Enemies. Which God of his infinite Mercy grant. I am, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wholly yours, as you are the Churches Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101060:5"/>
            <head>VOX CLERI: OR THE <hi>Senſe of the Clergy,</hi> CONCERNING ALTERATIONS in the Eſtabliſhed LITURGY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Intelligence you were pleaſed to give me of the Election of Dr. <hi>Jane</hi> to be Prolocutor of the Convocation, gives great ſatisfaction to the Clergy of theſe Parts; and that he was Choſen by much the major part of your Members, is lookt on as a good Omen of Succeſs in your Proceedings for the good of the Church, as by Law eſtabliſhed; He being generally known to be a Perſon extraordinarily well qualified, as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Parts and Piety<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as of Loyalty and Love to the Church. I have (as you deſired) been very ſolicitous to inform my ſelf concerning the Sentiments of the Clergy in my Neighbourhood, whether they think it convenient that there ſhould be Alterations made in the Liturgy, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Diſcipline of the Church, or not: And although I find them very inclinable to part with ſeveral Ceremonies, and to ſubmit to many Alterations for the peace of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101060:6"/>Church, and ſatisfaction of ſober Diſſenters; yet conſidering what weightier Matters the Diſſenters ſeek to remove, they ſuppoſe it more adviſable not to part with any thing to thoſe that will not be ſatisfied, unleſs they may carry all: And for this Opinion of theirs, which they humbly ſubmit to the more mature determination of the Convocation, they humbly offer the following Conſiderations:</p>
            <p n="1">1. They think it very reaſonable, that ſuch as are ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved ſhould make their Application to the Convocation, to whom His Majeſty hath given Power to prepare ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies as may by the Parliament receive the force of a Law; for ſo ſays the Commiſſion; So that the things by you ſo conſidered and prepared may be in a readineſs to be offered to the Convocation at their next meeting; and when ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by them, may be preſented to us, and our Two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament; that if it ſhall be judged fit, they may be eſtabliſhed in due form of Law. It cannot be expected that the ſeveral Sects ſhould agree in Common Propoſals, but that ſuch of them as will be ſatisfied with what in Reaſon and Conſcience may be granted, and then I ſhould not doubt that they would be gratified, and a good agreement made; for all agree (according to our Subſcriptions) that ſuch Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonis as concern Diſcipline and Order, may, upon juſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, be altered and changed; but whether Alterations ſhould be made when they are like to produce more hurt than good, is what we think worthy of conſideration in the preſent caſe. And we think we have a Moral aſſurance, that whatever Conceſſions the Convocation can make with ſafety to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, will not only be deſpiſed, but caſt back as filth in our faces; not only with a <hi>Quis requiſivit,</hi> but with a <hi>Pudet haec Opprobria vobis;</hi> as if our manner of publick Worſhip were ſo corrupt, that we were aſhamed of it, and were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of a neceſſity to purge it. Whereas though it was declared in the Preface to the Liturgy, as alſo in the King's
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101060:6"/>Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion, as is repeated <hi>p.</hi> 13. of that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>That it is reaſonable that on weighty and important Conſiderations, according to the Exigency of times and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſuch Changes and Alterations may be made, as to thoſe that are in place of Authority ſhould ſeem neceſſary or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient:</hi> Yet it is there ſaid, <hi>We are fully perſwaded in our Judgments, that the Book, as it ſtood before eſtabliſhed by Law, doth not contain in it any thing contrary to the Word of God, or to ſound Doctrine, or which a godly Man may not with a good Conſcience uſe and ſubmit unto, or which is not fairly defenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble againſt any that ſhall oppoſe the ſame.</hi> Though the Book there ſpoken of hath been altered for the better in ſome Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of places ſince that Declaration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They think it reaſonable, that the End ſhould be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, before the Means be reſolved on. Now the End de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the Alterations to be made, is the Satisfaction of the Conſciences of the Diſſenters, and reducing them to the Communion of the Church; but what thoſe Alterations are that will give them ſatisfaction, hath not yet been propoſed with any moderation, nor what Conceſſions will reduce them to our Communion. The Author of a Diſcourſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the late Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion, <hi>p.</hi> 18. ſaith, <hi>That in the Year</hi> 1661, <hi>the Alterations and Additions then made by the Convocation, did amount to the number of about Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred:</hi> Yet that Eſtabliſhed Liturgy was rejected by ſome of the chiefeſt Diſſenters (not without very indecent Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, who had promiſed to leave thoſe things to the Parliament and Convocation) with this reproach, <hi>If theſe be all the Abatements and Amendments ye will admit, ye ſell your own Innocency, and the Churches Peace for nothing.</hi> In the Year 1681, when Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> made large Overtures to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Diſſenters, <hi>(viz)</hi> That the Croſs in Baptiſm might be either taken off, or conſin'd to publick Baptiſm, and left to the choice of the Parents: That ſuch as could not Kneel
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101060:7"/>might be permitted to ſtand at the reception of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's Supper: That the Surplice ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away: That at Baptiſm the Fathers ſhould be permitted to joyn with the Sponſors in offering the Child to Baptiſm, or deſire them publickly to preſent their Child, and the Charge be given to them both: That they ſhould be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Subſcribe only to thirty ſix of the Articles: That there ſhould be a new Tranſlation of the Pſalms for Pariſh-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: That the Apocryphal Leſſons ſhould be exchanged for Scriptural: That the Rubrick ſhould be Corrected, with many other Condeſcentions. They were all thrown, as it were, with ſpite in his teeth, by thoſe that Anſwered his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Propoſals, with an <hi>Habeat ſibi &amp; ſuis.</hi> And in a Book of Mr. <hi>R. B</hi>'s, lately Re-printed, being an Account of Non-conformity in the Reigns of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second and <hi>James</hi> the Second; it is affirmed, That there are Forty ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Particulars in our Communion, beſides Thirty tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Principles and Circumſtantials, which affright the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters from it; and he reproacheth the Conformiſts as a company of lying and perjur'd Perſons. And the Author of a late Book, called the <hi>Healing Attempt,</hi> ſays, they (the Non-conformiſts) are not ſatisfied with the Propenſion of our Governors, to lay aſide the Ceremonies, and other more offenſive Impoſitions, unleſs their new Model for a Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion may be admitted; which is ſuch, as would make every Pariſh-Church independent, and in a ſhort time turn our <hi>Bethel</hi> into a <hi>Babel</hi> of Confuſion; whereas therefore it is ſaid in the Preface to the Liturgy, <hi>It is reaſonable, that on weighty and important Conſiderations, ſuch Alterations may be made as to thoſe that are in Authority ſhould ſeem neceſſary and convenient:</hi> Yet it is added in the ſame Preface, <hi>We are fully perſwaded in our Judgments (and we here profeſs it to the World, that the Book, as it ſtood before eſtabliſhed by Law</hi> (and we may ſay the ſame of the Book now Eſtabliſhed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Six hundred Alterations) <hi>doth not contain in it any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101060:7"/>thing contrary to the Word of God, or to ſound Doctrine, or which a godly Man may not with a good Conſcience uſe or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto, or which is not fairly defenſible against any that ſhall oppoſe the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I take it as granted, that the Convocation neither can nor will alter all thoſe Particulars which ſome leading Men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Diſſenters do account to be Sinful; nor all thoſe tremendous Circumſtantials which will ſtill afright them from our Communion; and that if but a few, if but one ſuch thing, which they account to be Sinful, remain unaltered, the Schiſm will ſtill be continued: and therefore if I ſhould ask, <hi>Cui bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no?</hi> To what end ſhould any Alterations be made? I doubt a ſatisfactory Anſwer could not be given by ſuch as plead for them, when they themſelves have ſo plainly declared, that they will not be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But herein we may pleaſe the King, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a great part of the Diſſenting Laity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt as to the King, His Majeſty hath devolved that Province on the Convocation and Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> He hath declared his Satisfaction as to the preſent Conſtitution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He doth confirm his delared Judgment by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice in Communicating with the Church as eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and frequent Promiſes to favour and protect it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the Parliament, they do generally live in the Communion of the Church; and if any do otherwiſe, it is contrary to ſeveral Acts of preceding Parliaments, againſt which, though a Toleration be their Security, yet as that hath been formerly exploded, ſo it may be again, and if they ſee it fit, abrogated.</p>
            <p>And <hi>4hly,</hi> Nothing can be obligatory but what ſhall be enacted by them whoſe conſent we are not aſſured of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the People, though ſome few may deſire Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, yet they do not agree in what Alterations they will acquieſce: And it is more probable, that the inſiſting on a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101060:8"/>Conſormity to the preſent Conſtitution, will reduce all to an Uniformity, rather than any intended Alterations; for Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſhews, that from the Year 1661, when Uniformity was enjoyned, the People were generally reduced to it; ſo as in ſome great Cities ſcarce three or four perſons of any note kept off from our Communion, until the Toleration (procured by the Papiſts) put all into Diſorder again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> What the late Commiſſioners have prepared in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to an Alteration, is to us a <hi>Non conſtat,</hi> the Reaſons are beſt known to themſelves; but though we have no very good opinion of ſuch of them as are ſaid to be of <hi>Latitudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Principles, yet they having hitherto lived in a Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Church as eſtabliſhed, we hope they will not give up any thing that is ſubſtantial, with the Circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als for Decency and Order; or if they do ſo, it will be as pardonable in us of the Country, to forſake them, as for ſome of thoſe eminent Divines, that were joyned in Commiſſion with them: And I am fully perſwaded, that on making ſuch Alterations as are ſaid to be prepared by the Commiſſioners, the Church will run the hazard of offending a greater number of more conſiderable perſons, than they are likely to gratifie thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But ſuch Alterations being made, ſuch as ſhall thenceforward continue to be Diſſenters, will be more inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is not very probable, becauſe they will ſtill ſay, you have only taken off the leſſer Offences, but have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the weighter Matters on their Conſciences ſtill, <hi>(viz.)</hi> ſuch as in their Conſciences they account to be Sinful, and their Conformity to them to be Damnable.</p>
            <p>And if after ſuch Alterations be eſtabliſhed by Law, and any Penalty be annexed for the Sanction of that Law, the Legiſlators will be reflected on as Perſecutors, and their Laws as ſo many tearing Engines: though I muſt needs ſay, there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet were ſuch ſevere Penalties enacted againſt any ſort of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101060:8"/>Diſſenters, though known to be Men of Atheiſtical and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchical Principles, as againſt ſome Reverend Fathers and Members of the Church, who are known to be Men of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Peaceable Principles, yet they quietly ſubmit with <hi>a Deus providebit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may well preſume, that no Man living in Communion with our Church, is convinc'd, that there is any thing Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in that Communion; now theſe being the greater and the better part, I ſay with Dr. <hi>Beveredge</hi> in his Sermon to the Convocation, p. 25. <hi>Neque ratio neque perpetua Eccleſiae conſuetudo patitur ut pars toti praeferatur;</hi> Neither reaſon, nor the perpetual Cuſtom of the Church, doth permit that a part ſhould be preferred before the whole: And then nothing can juſtify the Diſſenters from Schiſm in their Separation from us; for as to things that are by them judged Inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, it is fit that the greater and better Part ſhould judge of Expediency for the reſt, and not they for themſelves or their Betters: And if ſuch Opinionative and Ungovernable People were for a while, by ſtrict Diſcipline, taught the Duty of Self-denial, as to things in their nature indifferent, and how neceſſary Obedience to Superiours is in ſuch caſes, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven they themſelves do practice, and in which ſort of things only our Governours have Authority, we might hope for an Uniformity, and not otherwiſe: And to this end it is very obſervable what Dr. <hi>Beveredge</hi> ſays in his Sermon, p. 26. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquas novis mutare Legibus;</hi> To change old Laws for new, is alway dangerous, unleſs ſuch a Neceſſity conſtrain as is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe inſuperable.</p>
            <p>There was never any Church which hath not inſerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Laws many things (not contrary, but) beſide thoſe things which are in the Holy Scripture, and having made ſuch Laws, do eſtabliſh them by the Sanctions of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Puniſhments, <hi>p.</hi> 23: When therefore that Learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſays, p. 27. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum Eccleſiae noſlra, &amp;c.</hi> whether our Church be obliged by a Neceſſity to change any thing that is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101060:9"/>by her Laws eſtabliſhed, is not his part to determine; but, <hi>Prudentis est,</hi> and immediately adds, <hi>This only I dare to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That if it be neceſſary to reduce wandring Sheep into Christ's Flock; if to take off Scruples from the minds of weak Brethren; if to allay Hatred, appeaſe Anger, and as much as may be, to ſuppreſs all Diſſentions concerning Religion; if to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline to its Primitive Vigour; if to Defend and Eſtabliſh the best Church in the World against the Aſſaults of Men and Devils; if theſe things</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſeem neceſſary to any Man, it will alſo ſeem neceſſary to that Man to admit ſuch Changes as he is perſwaded will conduce to ſuch ends; ſo as the Change be made in ſuch things only which our Church hath conſtituted by her ſole Authority, not in ſuch as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church by her common Laws hath Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then we ſay, that to alter the Epiſcopal Government, to take the Power of Ordination from Biſhops, and place it in the hands of Presbyters, to take away a Well-ordered Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, and bring in Extemporary Prayers for Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to give every Miniſter a Juriſdiction and Power of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and many other things, without which ſome grave Diſſenters will not be comprehended, is more than the Learned Doctor will grant: for of ſuch things he ſpeaks his mind impartially, <hi>Has ſub quovis praetextu vel extremis digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis attingere, &amp;c.</hi> To endeavour the removal of theſe, under any pretence whatſoever, or to touch them with one of our Fingers, is contrary to the Religious Care of all the Churches of God, and of our own.</p>
            <p>And to Abrogate or Reject that, which hath been every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and at all times obſerved, is not to change an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Rite only, but the Church itſelf, and to make it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from all other Churches of God.</p>
            <p>But what then is the Doctor's Judgment concerning ſuch Conſtitutions as are in the Power of a particular Church.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101060:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This the Doctor determined, p. 23. <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, p. 26. <hi>A Change hath neither been wont, nor ought to be made by any Church at any time, unleſs ſome great Neceſſity do conſtrain thereto:</hi> But of a change of what fort of Laws doth the Doctor ſpeak? That he tells us in the ſame Page, <hi>Neque enim quiſpiam, &amp;c.</hi> There is not any Man ſo skilful, as by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Art to foreſee how many and great dangers are like to ariſe by the change of incommodious Laws; wherefore to change old Laws for new, is alway dangerous, unleſs ſuch a neceſſity urge it as cannot otherwiſe be overcome; and ſuch as is ſo manifeſt to all, that whoever ſeeth the Change, may alſo ſee, <hi>Summam ejus rationem &amp; neceſſitatem,</hi> the greateſt Reaſon and neceſſity for the Change even of thoſe incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Laws.</p>
            <p>To this I ſhall need to add no more than that apt Alluſion of this Learned Doctor, concerning the Obligation of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws, p. 19. <hi>As in this Kingdom there are many Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations and inferiour Societies which have a Power granted them, of conſtituting Laws for themſelves and their Members, with this caution, That nothing be done or conſtituted by them which is contrary to the Statutes of the Realm, the Common Law, or any ancient Cuſtom, which beyond the memory of Man, hath been introduced and received by the whole Kingdom, and thereby hath obtained the force of a Law;</hi> (Now though this be in <hi>p.</hi> 20. applied to the Univerſal Church, yet in <hi>p.</hi> 21.) the Doctor applies it to particular Churches: <hi>In quacunque provincia ſitae ſunt;</hi> In whatever Province a Church is plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Biſhops and Paſtors of that Province, may, as oft as occaſion requires, hold their Synods or Sacred Aſſemblies to deliberate and conſult of things belonging to the Church conſtituted in that Province: And p. 22. <hi>All ſuch Churches, by their Synods, have power to make Laws, as they ſhall judge expedient for the better Adminiſtration of the Publick Worſhip of God, and of his Word and Sacraments, within their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; otherwiſe it could not well be, that any Provincial or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101060:10"/>National Church ſhould long ſubſist, or be at peace.</hi> And p. 23. <hi>Moreover, it belongs to all the Churches of God, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh, by Eccleſiaſtical Penalties, ſuch Canons by them made, lest any thing contrary to them ſhould be without Impunity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But our Diviſions had almoſt betrayed us to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Slavery, for prevention of which danger, for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is adviſeable, as much as may be, to inlarge the Terms of our Communion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But who betrayed us to thoſe Diviſions? were they not ſuch as cauſeleſly ſeparated from us, and were more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to joyn with the common Enemy of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, though they call'd themſelves true Proteſtants, than with the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Whereof he that wrote the Defence of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Sermon of Separation, gave an Account, and even dared the Opponents to call him to the proof of it, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> &amp;c. were entertain'd as Penſioners to the late King, and by him encouraged to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our Diviſions; by which the Papiſts got great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages againſt us. And whereto tended the flattering and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Addreſſes of the Sectaries to the late King, to ſtand by him with their Lives and Fortunes, and to obey him without Reſerve, but to continue thoſe Diviſions, and foment thoſe Seeds of Diſcord which were grown up, and ripen'd almoſt for the Harveſt, to cut us all down, and utterly deſtroy us? And what if ſome leading Presbyterians be by our Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons let into the Church, and advanced to ſuch Preferments as they hope for; to be Biſhops, Deans, Arch-deacons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what ſecurity have we, that they will not promote Diviſions in the Church, more dangerous, than the Schiſm they made by Separation from us; as ſome Biſhops, and others that had been ſour'd with that Leaven, being preferred in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, did attempt: A ſecret Enemy within the Walls of a well Fortified City, is more dangerous than an open Foe in the Field.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101060:10"/>
            <p>I have read in the Life of Judge <hi>Hales,</hi> written by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> p. 71. That there was a Bill for Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehenſion contrived by Biſhop <hi>Wilkins,</hi> Sir <hi>Orlando Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and that Judge, which though it contained more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Terms than what are now propoſed, (as I have been informed) for the Admiſſion of ſome Diſſenters into our Communion, yet it was oppoſed by the Clergy, becauſe they thought a Faction within the Church, would prove to be more hurtful than a Schiſm without it: And when one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was let in upon Terms not perhaps unreaſonable, another Party, upon other Terms leſs reaſonable, would ſolicite their Admiſſion. And it was objected, That as ſome might come in, ſo others, that were in our Communion, might take Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by the Alterations, and deſert it; and ſeeing our fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Changes in ſome things, they might ſuppoſe that there is nothing certain among us; and from the many Diſputes about our Liturgy, proceed to queſtion our Articles, and at laſt fall off to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which they ſaw more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to their Principles: For which, and other reaſons the Bill was caſt out by the Votes of the Houſe of Commons, with whom the ſame Conſiderations may ſtill prevail.</p>
            <p>And now let the Men that are given to Change, produce thoſe weighty and important Reaſons, required in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Common-Prayer, or that great Neceſſity which Dr. <hi>Beveredge</hi> requires for the Alteration, even of incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Laws.</p>
            <p>Is it neceſſary that an honeſt Man ſhould voluntarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign his Freehold to a litigious Perſon, who neither deſires nor deſerves it, and perhaps would improve the poſſeſſion of it to his ruine?</p>
            <p>Is it neceſſary that a Parent ſhould yeild to a diſobedient Child, upon his own unreaſonable terms?</p>
            <p>Is it neceſſary that a good Man ſhould accuſe, bear falſe witneſs againſt, and condemn and execute himſelf, and be a <hi>Felo de ſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101060:11"/>
            <p>Is it neceſſary that the Citizens ſhould ſuffer a breach to be made in their Wall, to give advantage to an Enemy, when they are ready to open their Gates to let in any that offers a reaſonable aſſurance that he is a Friend?</p>
            <p>Is there any neceſſity to Reform that Church which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeft to be the beſt Reformed Church in the World; that Church to whoſe Pattern all the reſt do deſire, and only want power and opportunity to conform their own?</p>
            <p>Is it neceſſary we ſhould do more for thoſe, who wilfully departed from us, and as our Saviour intimates, Not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be with us, were againſt us, than we have done for thoſe forreign Proteſtants, Men of great Learning and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, who voluntarily offer themſelves to our Communion, without inſiſting on any Terms with us?</p>
            <p>Is it neceſſary that a Church in which all things neceſſary to Salvation, may be freely enjoyed, ſhould accuſe herſelf of want of Chriſtian Charity, and of impoſing ſuch ſinful Terms, for admitting others into her Communion, as were purpoſely deſigned to keep them out, and afterward voluntarily caſt off thoſe things, and thereby confeſs themſelves guilty of ſo great Uncharitableneſs?</p>
            <p>Is it neceſſary that a Church, which hath Authority to judge for itſelf, what is decent and orderly, ſhould ſubject herſelf to the Judgment of her Members, to determine for her or themſelves, what is decent and expedient, and what is not; eſpecially when the Exception from Obedience to the Church in ſuch things, ought to be as evident and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable, as the Command to obey them in ſuch Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is?</p>
            <p>Is it neceſſary that we ſhould give greater Offence to the Papiſts, from coming into our Communion (now in this juncture of time) by our Variableneſs and Defect of the Solemnity of Publick Worſhip, which hitherto they have objected againſt us?</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101060:11"/>
            <p>Is it neceſſary we ſhould part with any thing to them, whom we have reaſon to ſuſpect, that they will not leave craving till they have all?</p>
            <p>When all theſe things are proved to be neceſſary, then ſhall we be ready to make Alterations in our Ceremonies, and other Circumſtances, if the Diſſenters will be content to let us injoy what is ſubſtantial and neceſſary to the well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Church: In the mean time we ſhall account our ſelves Happy, in the number of thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, that know when they are well.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101060:12"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS ON A DISCOURSE CONCERNING The Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have alſo conferred with my Brethren concerning a Book intituled, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion,</hi> 1689. Of which we ſhall not ſay ſo much as the Author doth of a former Commiſſion for the like affair, <hi>viz. That he never entertain'd a good Opinion of it.</hi> We only remark, that this Author hath laid the foundation, which he and ſome others have framed their ſuperſtructure on, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That the Alterations intended by it are not prejudicial.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That they are uſeful, tending to the well-being of the Church.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That it is a fit juncture for putting the deſign in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Author gives ſeveral Inſtances of ſeveral Alterations made, as in the Third of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-book was compoſed and altered, the 1ſt. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> And a Proclamation for Authorizing an Uniformity of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101060:12"/>Book of Common-Prayer; and at the Return of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, the Liturgy was reviewed (and altered) by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ae the <hi>Savoy;</hi> but our Author takes no notice of the Penalties to be inflicted on ſuch as ſhould not conform to it, and on ſuch as ſhould defame it, by ſeveral Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor how little effect it had for the healing the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Schiſm which ſome Diſſenters had then made; nor how much King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt was diſpleaſed with thoſe Diſſenters, that pretended to make good their Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, which they were not able to perform in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> whereof the Author ſpeaks, <hi>p.</hi> 3. Yet this I ſay of this Author, that he ſpeaks much more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly than the Author of <hi>A Glance on the Eccleſiaſtical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> who would precipitate the matter, and have an Act of Parliament for a Comprehenſion firſt, and then an Act to Authorize the Commiſſion: But our Author pretends only to prepare things, thereby to ſave Time and Labour, in kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Convocation; whatever the Pretence be, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence may be very prejudicial to the Members of the Convocation, if any difference ſhould happen for this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and ſeveral Letters being diſperſed into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where they have their Reſidence, to prepoſſeſs the Minds of Diſſenters, that they have occaſioned the obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the intended Union; and as thoſe Letters import, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be treated as Enemies.</p>
            <p>That Mobile which are already too full of Rankor againſt them, and have already, in a conſiderable City, burnt a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop inſtead of a Pope, will be ready to affront them, and throw them into the next fire, as they were, when there was rejoycing for the Biſhops deliverance out of the <hi>Tower:</hi> And therefore it had been more prudent, if they had with patience expected the determination of the Convocation, and forborn thoſe ill-boding Reflections, which tend to create an Odium againſt ſuch Members; though it be well known, they have no power to offer any thing, being limited by the King's Propoſals.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101060:13"/>
            <p>Nor hath the Author conſulted better for his own Party, when ſpeaking of the Perſonal Qualifications of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, <hi>p.</hi> 8. he tells the Country, how they have been tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced as aſſuming Men, who will think themſelves bound in Honour to defend what they ſhall have done, as Men that have tenderneſs enough to part with any thing but their Church-preferments; As Men who have a Latitude to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to a Church, <hi>de facto,</hi> which hath Power on its ſide. And <hi>pag.</hi> 9. Men who conceal their own inclinations, till it is time to ſhew them; Men likely to do the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> a good turn, when opportunity ſerves, and which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they imagine now they have, which Characters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree well with thoſe who are known to be <hi>Latitudinarians</hi> indeed, and have Monopolized Church-preferments. Yet our Author ſays they have no temptation now to ſhew, that they are Men of Latitude; it ſeems then they had heretofore. <hi>Page</hi> 10. our Author mentioneth another Objection, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That as it may happen, our Church may be changed, alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and transformed by nine Men, which are the number of the <hi>Quorum</hi> in the Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Now although I dare not ſay, there was any partiality uſed in naming the Commiſſioners; yet when I conſider that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe that were named did not appear, and ſome very conſiderable perſons that did appear, perceiving that ſome ſuch things, as might in their judgment prove prejudicial to the Church, were propoſed, did diſſent and withdraw; it was not altogether unlikely that Nine of thoſe who remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed might prepare ſuch things, as the Convocation would not approve of, as the Event will ſhew.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe great and excellent Men, who, as our Author ſays, are not named in the Commiſſion; it had been a more commendable Office and Duty to have pleaded on their behalf, knowing them to be Men of great Prudence and Fortitude, as well as of Integrity and Affection to the Church; and that they are never like to diſturb the Peace of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101060:13"/>the State, to intercede that ſome favour might be ſhewn to them as well as to Diſſenters: Seeing if any, they are the Men, who ſuffer for ſake of their Conſciences; eſpecially, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Author ſays, <hi>The Commiſſioners deſign nothing ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable as to fear, that the Alterations would not paſs in a free Convocation, if thoſe Reverend and Judicious Prelates were preſent.</hi> But it is our great unhappineſs, that though there have been ſeveral Convocations called, yet had not an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of meeting, till theſe Right Reverend Fathers and others were excluded and made uncapable; what hinderance this may be to the performance of what they promiſed, (as our Author relates) <hi>That they wanted no due tenderneſs to Diſſenters, but were willing to come to ſuch a temper as ſhould be thought fit when that matter ſhould be conſidered in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Convocation,</hi> I cannot divine, but acquieſce in the judgment of our Author, That if nothing unreaſonable were deſigned, it might then have paſſed, and a firm Eſtabliſhment enſued; for doubtleſs the calm Tempers of thoſe Reverend Fathers would mightily have influenced their Sons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 13. mention is made of the Commiſſion; the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face whereof is the ſame with what hath been before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the Preface to the Liturgy, concerning the Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Rites and Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon weighty and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Conſiderations; and the end of it is, to take away all occaſions of differences for the future, as well as reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all Their Majeſties Subjects at preſent. A Bleſſing! this to be ſeriouſly endeavoured by all perſons, but rather to be hoped for than expected; for though not only all our Rites and Ceremonies, all things tending to Decency and Order, ſhould be taken away, yet there will be ſome that will find occaſions of difference ſtill; for we are told in the late <hi>Healing Attempt, That it is impoſſible for the Diſſenters to unite, if it be ſtill affirmed, That the Biſhops and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are not of the ſame Order: That the Power of Ordination is the ſole Prerogative of the Biſhops: (i. e.)</hi> If the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101060:14"/>by Presbyters be not as authentick, as that by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; or that the Ordination by Presbyters is void; and that the Ordaining them again by Biſhops, is not Re-ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and he tells us plainly, <hi>That it is not the taking away of our Ceremonies, and other Impoſitions, that will ſatisfie the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters; but if a Comprehenſion may not be had on thoſe other terms, there can be none at all.</hi> And a greater Diſſenter than he ſays of Epiſcopacy, <hi>That it is that thorny hedge which he had made his buſineſs to pull down and would endeavour it (by going on both ſides) as long as he lived.</hi> And what diſlike ſome have, not only of the pretended defects in our Liturgy, but to any Liturgy for publick Worſhip, is too well known by ſome very late Writings of the Diſſenters. And Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> affirms, <hi>That of the Forty ſinful Terms for a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us, if Thirty-nine were taken away, and only that Rubrick concerning the Salvation of Infants, dying ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after their Baptiſm were continued, yet they could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to what purpoſe ſhould we begin, when we cannot ſee where to end. Is it not better to endure ſome inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies (as in all Conſtitutions ſome will be) than to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves to certain miſchiefs? And what can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect when the Six hundred Alterations in 1661, had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent effect, but were rejected with ſcorn? I wonder how this Author can object to you, as if you proceeded on the ſame falſe grounds, as thoſe Papiſts <hi>Heath</hi> and <hi>Fecknam</hi> did in <hi>Primo Eliz.</hi> in oppoſing the Act for Uniformity, <hi>(viz.) That thoſe changes were departures from the Standard of the Catholick Church; That Points once defined, were not to be brought again into queſtion; That the Church ſhould be conſtant to it ſelf:</hi> For he cannot but know that they oppoſed the Act for Uniformity <hi>Primo Eliz.</hi> as excluding the falſe Doctrines and Superſtitions of <hi>Rome;</hi> whereas we plead for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Uniformity in Doctrine, Worſhip and Government, which are all oppoſed by ſome ſort of Diſſenters: I ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101060:14"/>leave the indifferent Reader to judge of the Inference which he makes, <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>That if the Commiſſioners in</hi> 1661, <hi>ſaw rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for making Additions and Alterations to the number of Six hundred; That there is equal, if not greater reaſon for ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improvements.</hi> I think he might rather conclude, as he doth immediately after; That if they had foreſeen what is ſince come to paſs, <hi>(viz.)</hi> how few of the Diſſenters came in upon thoſe Condeſcentions) they would not have done all that they did. And perhaps on theſe Conceſſions, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Diſſenters, the Papiſts had thoſe hopes cheriſhed in them (of which our Author there ſpeaks) of Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the removal of the Sanguinary, and then of other Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws, and of Forty Chappels to be opened for them in and about <hi>London;</hi> for they know the Charity of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not confined to one Sect, as that of the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries is. What he ſays <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>That the Conformiſts have given their Aſſent and Conſent to the Book of Common-Prayer, whereof the Preface is a part; which ſays, That in Churches Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials may from time to time admit of Alteration,</hi> is true, but not the whole truth; for it is added, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon great and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Reaſons,</hi> which the Author omits; and if he ſpeaks it not, as being in a good Mood, but as his ſetled Judgment, that our Church, as it is the beſt conſtituted Church in the World; then certainly they that cannot conform to our Church, muſt on the ſame reaſon diſſent from all the other Reformed Churches. <hi>Page</hi> 20. he ſays, <hi>He is, in part, of the Opinion that the Prayers cannot be altered for the better by any meer humane compoſition:</hi> But he will not grant it of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Collect; and what thoſe Collects are, we may have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to conſider hereafter; it is enough, that our conſtant daily Prayers are beyond exception; His great buſineſs (as he calls it) will be but a great burthen to the Diſſenters, as well as himſelf, <hi>(viz.) Adding ſome Offices to the Liturgy, and preparing new ones which are wanting.</hi> Seeing we have had ſo many complaints of the length and tediouſneſs of them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101060:15"/>formerly, one thing the Author can ſcarce pardon himſelf for, when writing of thoſe who he ſays ſo angrily, though cauſeleſly, ſpake againſt that Work, <hi>i. e.</hi> of making Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; he adds, <hi>They muſt pardon me, if ſo near after the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of them, I take notice of the</hi> French <hi>Papiſts, who have reviled both the Commiſſion, and the perſons named in it.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſcems to joyn all ſuch as are not for Alterations, with the Papiſts; and whether they muſt pardon him for this, if the People deal with them as Papiſts, let him conſider, and pardon himſelf if he can; yet I think the Papiſts would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willingly have us make more Alterations, than moſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants think ſit to make.</p>
            <p>It is a pretty inſinuation which he makes, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>That the Conformiſts will naturally be glad if the Houſe, in which they reſolve to live and dye, have all the ſtrength and beauty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it, which can be given it by Commiſſion, Convocation, and Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſtrength and beauty which it now hath, is by all thoſe means confirmed to them; and willingly they would live, and hope they may happily dye in it: But if the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters will make breaches in that Houſe, and take poſſeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, deface its Beauty, and undermine its Strength, and force them to leave it, I cannot ſee how they can naturally be glad of the behaviour of ſuch ill-natur'd Men; and that there are ſome ſuch beſides thoſe whom I have mentioned alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the Author ſpeaks of ſome in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> and I know ſuch in other Counties, who oblige their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, and have vowed themſelves never to return to the Communion of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and if the preſent generation be ſo bad, the next is not like (if theſe Men have their deſire) to be better.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 22. the Author conſiders, <hi>That now is a fit juncture of time for Alterations:</hi> And his firſt ground is, <hi>the Expediency, for things which may be done,</hi> yet are not to be done at a time when they are not expedient: And thus he ſhews the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101060:15"/>Expediency; <hi>The Paſſions of Men at this time are in a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fermentation; and he that would allay the Feaver, may ſtay too long, if he forbears to preſcribe till the bloud is quiet.</hi> But muſt the Mother be bleeded, if the Children be diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered? Muſt the Paſſions of Men diſturb the Peace of the Church, and no Man endeavour to ſuppreſs them? If a ſick Man be diſtempered, and ungovernable, the Phyſician is his friend, though he cauſe him to be confin'd or bound for a time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He ſays the Church hath at this time powerful Enemies.</hi> Therefore I think ſhe ought to ſtand on her guard, and keep ſtrict watch, leaſt they that are ſo, make too near approaches. And none are more dangerous, than thoſe that are or have been of the ſame Houſe; And though the Church had of late as implacable Enemies as ever, and they in great Power; yet, by the bleſſing of God, ſhe hath out-lived them.</p>
            <p>Obj. 3. <hi>Their Majeſties have declared their deſires of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Commiſſion ſays, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon weighty and important Reaſons; and that the Alterations prepared by the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, may be approved by the Convocation and Parliament.</hi> Cannot you wait for that time?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their Majeſties deſire may be beſt known by their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Communion of the Church as now eſtabliſhed, and his former and late Declarations to favour and protect it; for which the Convocation have addreſſed their Thanks, and doubt not of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Houſe of Lords have given us their Senſe of it in the Bill of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We muſt expect their Senſe, nothing being as yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by them, as to new Alterations; and the Act for Uniformity ſtands unrepealed by them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Toleration is already granted by Statute</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is a greater favour than was granted to the Church-party, in the late Wars, for almoſt Twenty years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, when Diſſenters were in Power; and that ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice them which they accounted too much for others.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101060:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. It is well known at whoſe inſtance, and for whoſe ſake Tolerations were formerly granted, <hi>(viz.)</hi> of ſuch as were profeſſed Papiſts, and that under a falſe pretence, That the preſſing of Uniformity had not procured the deſired ſucceſs; but the true Reaſon was, that it was too ſucceſsful.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Reaſons given by a very Religious and Loyal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament againſt Toleration are irrefragable, which were paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi> in the Parliament 1662, and may be ſeen in ſeveral Printed Tracts: This Parliament in the Act for Uniformity, did as much as was poſſible to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Liturgy then Eſtabliſhed, to future Generations, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all Deans and Chapters to procure Copies of it under the Great Seal, and perfect Copies of the Act of Uniformity; and the like were to be kept in the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> that by them, any Error committed by the Printer might be rectified.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Eyes of the World are upon us, and all the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches are in expectation of ſomething to be done, which may make for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Eyes of the Chriſtian World admire, as well the Holineſs of our Doctrine, as the Beauty of our Worſhip and Adminiſtration; as alſo, the great things that God hath done for our Church to preſerve it, as hitherto, (bleſſed be his Name) he hath graciouſly done againſt all the violent Attempts of Popiſh Fury, and Fanatick Zeal. And as for the great Numbers of <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, which are now among us, if we conſult them, they will all acknowledge the great Goodneſs of God, in preſerving our Church to be a Sanctuary unto them, from the Rage of their Perſecutors; and heartily joyn with us in all our Ordinances, without any ſcruple againſt either our Doctrine or Ceremonies. And this gives us much eaſe under our domeſtick Troubles, and hopes that it will be a benefit to us, if well conſidered by them that are otherwiſe minded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No Man can be wiſe too late,</hi> (ſaith our Author) <hi>pag.</hi> 24.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101060:16"/>But it's too late to ſhut the Stable-door, when the Steed is ſtollen: <hi>Principiis obſta,</hi> is a wiſe Rule. <hi>Page</hi> 25. <hi>After the Year</hi> 1661, <hi>though there were Writs iſſued out for a Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet no Warrant could be procured for the Support and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the Church, during the Reigns of</hi> Charles <hi>the Second, and</hi> James <hi>the Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The reaſon was, becauſe the Diſſenters of all ſorts ſeared what would be done in the Caſe of Toleration and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, as now they do in the Caſe of Comprehenſion, and therefore the Meeting was delayed. And he thinks it no good Advice of them that ſay, Do nothing now, or as little as may be: when little or much is not the buſineſs; but as much as is fit, he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon great and important Reaſons.</hi> He adds, <hi>If one Opportunity be neglected, it may diſcourage the Powers that offer it, from vouchſafing another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have heard indeed, That if the intended Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be not made by the Convocation, it may be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them in time. If ſo, it will be their comfort, that they did not put their Hands to the pulling down the Church up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own Heads. In the mean time, we of the Country are much amuſed to hear of your tedious Adjournments, and know not what to gueſs at, as the occaſion of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays; unleſs it be, to give the Diſſenters time to ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad ſcandalous Reports of ſuch of the Convocation that carried the Election of Dr. <hi>Jane</hi> to be Prolocutor, againſt thoſe who Voted for Dean <hi>Tillotſon;</hi> who, as we have heard, claimed it as his Right, belonging to that Deanary; though we have been ſince informed, that there belongs to that Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary only <hi>Jus dirigendi Electionem;</hi> which implies, That the Convocation had the Power and Right of Election; and that Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> was not then confirmed in that Deanary; but that the Election was carried only by three or four Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and given up by Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Party to prevent any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance: But you have aſſured us, that it was otherwiſe, there being Two to One who Voted for Dr. <hi>Jane.</hi> And now
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101060:17"/>that we ſee Letter after Letter ſent abroad, to caſt an Odium on ſuch as ſhall not Vote for Alterations, though they ſee not any ſufficient cauſe ſo to do, but great and important Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the contrary, we think that we ſee the reaſon of your Adjournments, which have given a Month's time to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to prepare and diſperſe ſuch Pamphlets as may tend to your prejudice, and prepoſſeſs the People, that you are the Enemies of Peace and Reconciliation; and to this end he complains: Firſt, (as the uſual Practice is) of thoſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who by means of any Letters or Pamphlets, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uncharitable Miſrepreſentations of the Commiſſioners, or the Work under their hands, are prejudiced againſt them; for he condemns ſuch as Enemies to Peace, and as having a Zeal not according to Knowledge: but neither this Author, nor any other, ſince the firſt meeting of the Convocation, have taken any care to prevent the prejudices that ſome have endeavoured to raiſe againſt the far greateſt part of them, for chuſing Dr. <hi>Jane,</hi> rather than Dean <hi>Tillotſon;</hi> and whereas we have not yet ſeen one Pamphlet, or Printed Letter to perſwade us, that there is no neceſſity of Alterations, we have very many, that not without great Zeal, would incline us to think them neceſſary. And this Work being done by way of preparation, our hope is, that the Convocation will meet with no more Adjournments, but cloſely apply themſelves to what ſhall be propoſed by their Majeſties, and give the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Reſult of their Conſultations, and the Reaſons of them: And ſo I joyn with the Author, earneſtly beſeeching the People, not to give too open an Ear to any ſuch Cenſures of Things, which they do not yet fully underſtand, and which for ought they know, may prove a great Bleſſing to them.</p>
            <p>The next Paper whereof I ſhall give you my thoughts, is, <hi>A Letter from a Miniſter in the Country, to a Member of the Convocation:</hi> The Author needed not have told us, that he was a Country-Miniſter; for though there be in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101060:17"/>many Miniſters, who for their Learning, may be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſparagement, compared with moſt of the City-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; yet the Matter of his Letter, as it is penned, ſhews, that he is inferiour to many of our Country-Miniſters, as will evidently appear, by his handling the particulars which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves any remark: He begins with what, he underſtands, will be firſt offered to the Convocation, (to wit) <hi>The Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Kalender;</hi> where he would have the Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal Leſſons exchanged, for as many taken out of the Canon of Scripture, as by the Biſhops and other Divines Aſſembled to conſider of that matter, 1641: He doth not ſay was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed; for I find in an Anſwer to a Petition preſented to the King's Majeſty, by above a Thouſand Miniſters, as it was there ſaid, that there was no ſuch conceſſion made; for <hi>pag.</hi> 14. the Anſwer to the Objection ſays, <hi>That they are groſly ignorant if they know it not, or wilfully malicious and turbulent, if knowing it to be lawful, they yet oppugne the Reading of the Apocryphal Writings in the Church; Non ad confirmationem fidei ſed ad reformationem morum:</hi> As the Ancient Fathers ſpeak and approve; for which they quote <hi>Hier.</hi> Preface in <hi>Pro. Cyprian</hi> in <hi>Symb.</hi> in whoſe days, it ſeems, they were ſo read. And they add, That the Articles of Convocation, and the Preface before the Apocryphal Books in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bibles, do directly ſhew; adding, that they give light to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Hiſtory. And in the Account given of the Proceedings of the Commiſſioners, Printed 1661, where the ſame Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was made, <hi>p.</hi> 55. and the reaſon given for it: <hi>Becauſe the Scriptures contain all things neceſſary, either in Doctrine to be believed, or in Duty to be practiſed:</hi> They anſwer, <hi>That ſuch a Reaſon would exclude all Sermons, as well as Apocrypha; And why then ſo many Sermons, if notwithſtanding the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Scripture, Sermons be neceſſary? There is no reaſon why theſe Apocryphal Leſſons ſhould not be uſeful, most of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining excellent Diſcourſes, and Rules of Morality: It is hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to be wiſhed, that Sermons were as good; and to leave
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101060:18"/>them out, were to croſs the Practice of the Church in former Ages.</hi> And the Reply of the Diſſenters at that time is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable: <hi>We asked not,</hi> ſay they, <hi>that no Apocryphal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter may be read in the Church; but, that none may be read as Leſſons.</hi> If you cite the Apocrypha as you do other Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Writings, or read them as Homilies, we ſpeak not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; and of this, neither thoſe Diſſenters, nor any ordinary Country-Miniſter could be ignorant; the Church having declared, That they are not of equal Authority with the Scriptures; which is known to their own People, who therefore will not have them Bound with their Bibles; beſides, no part of the Apocrypha is read on <hi>Sundays,</hi> but on the Week-days, when there are too few to hear them, and thoſe few better inſtructed than to think them Canonical. But though this may ſatisfie all ſober perſons, yet I do here proteſt, That were it not that the Diſſenters have given us an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that tho' theſe and many other Alterations ſhould be made, it would give them no ſatisfaction, nor bring them into our Communion, I would uſe all the Intereſt I have for ſuch Alterations; and for that end alſo, part with many of the Ceremonies; but of this there is a deep ſilence, or rather a loud diſſent.</p>
            <p>The Letter adds, <hi>If thoſe Apocryphal Chapters were ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read, ſo were</hi> Hermes Paſtor, <hi>and</hi> Clemens Rom. <hi>and the Argument holds for reading theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Church have anciently diſuſed them; but if they were now read, or the Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Polycarp,</hi> or ſome ſelect Chapters out of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, inſtead of the Sermons on the Week-days <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures;</hi> in which many greater Abſurdities tending to Schiſm and Sedition are injected into the minds of the People; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, it would be much more for the Edification of them.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If they,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>the Apocryphal Lectures, were read, then we know what Miſchief enſued from it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We know too, what Miſchief accidentally aroſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101060:18"/>from Reading the Scriptures; muſt they therefore be laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide? <hi>But the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath made them Canonical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The People do believe, that many of thoſe falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, many Falſhoods, and dangerous Opinions, which are held forth to them in their Conventicles, are as true as the Goſpel; and why are not they laid aſide? when we know what Miſchiefs ſome Sermons Preached in 41, and 42 produced: <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> with <hi>Tobit</hi> and his <hi>Dog</hi> could not have done ſuch diſmal feats. The next thing inſiſted on, <hi>p.</hi> 6. is, The <hi>Reviſing of the Pſalter, added to the Liturgy, which ſeems not ſo defenſible, there being a more Correct Copy in our Hands; and an inconſiſtancy between the two Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being obſerved by the Vulgar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though there be Variations in the two Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet they do not contradict one the other; but rather explain and give light to each other; as the divers Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of Learned Men do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Tranſlation of the Liturgy-Pſalter is taken moſtly from the Septuagint, or <hi>Greek</hi> Copies, which that Church ſtill obſerves; and it is obſervable, that our Saviour and the Apoſtles, when they quote the Scripture of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to confirm their Doctrine, do frequently make uſe of this Tranſlation, though the <hi>Hebrew</hi> was as well known to them as the <hi>Greek.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There are <hi>Variae Lectiones</hi> even in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies, which the want of Points hath occaſioned; concerning which there are yet great Diſputes among the Learned Criticks.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The beſt Tranſlations have many Defects and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtancies, occaſioned by the various Significations of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> words; as the word <hi>Barach</hi> ſignifies both to Bleſs and to Curſe: So that though the one ſhould be granted to be more correct than the other, yet becauſe the one ſerves as a ſhort Paraphraſe to explain the other, and the People have the Uſe of both, this Exception is a meer Cavil: And there is ſome weight in what the Letter obſerves, <hi>That the People have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101060:19"/>of them learnt the Pſalms, as they are daily read</hi> Memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>which if diſuſed, they would ſoon forget.</hi> And for this cauſe our Saviour made uſe of the Septuagint Tranſlation, becauſe it was beſt known to that Generation. And if the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint Tranſlation needs a Review, ſo doth the other, which is not ſo Correct, but it may be amended in many places, and ſo will the beſt, to the end of the World. That the Author of the Letter may let nothing paſs, he omits not the Uſe of the <hi>Ring in Marriage;</hi> tho' he ſays, <hi>It is agreed to be but a Civil Right:</hi> And therefore I leave him to be civilly treated by the Women.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 8. The Letter comes to treat of our <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which he ſays, <hi>There is a difficulty to proceed in our Diſſentions; for without quitting or altering, the Diſſenting Party is not to be brought into the Church;</hi> and without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining them, many of our own will hardly be kept in it: And he conſiders, <hi>That the one may occaſion a Schiſm from the Church, the other a Schiſm in it.</hi> Now a Schiſm in the Church, will tend more certainly and ſpeedily to its Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, than that out of the Church. And this Schiſm is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in being, and will not be remedied, tho' all the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies ſhould be taken away; it is therefore very impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, cauſleſly to begin another Schiſm in the Church, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it is not ſo much Conſcience, as Scruple and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, on which the Diſſenters diſlike our Ceremonies; for when for their Intereſt, and enjoyment of beneficial Offices, they were required to conform to the Publick Worſhip, they did it, notwithſtanding the Uſe of Ceremonies; and I know few of them who are not willing that their Children and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations ſhould conform for their advantage; and therefore I ſhall not trouble the Reader with his impracticable Idea's for Accommodation, and only ſay, That more than what he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth hath been offered for an Accommodation, but refuſed, and that not without ſcorn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 9. He comes to the buſineſs of <hi>Reordination,</hi> and ſays,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101060:19"/>
               <hi>They that have been Ordained by Presbyters (though they are not againſt Epiſcopal Orders, yet) think it unlawful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them, and to be Reordained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This he confeſſeth to be againſt a late Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment yet in force, which hath provided, <hi>That none are to be admitted to Officiate in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>without Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Ordination:</hi> for which reaſon, if there were no other, I cannot ſee how any Member of the Convocation can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it: The firſt Reaſon which the Letter gives for it, is, <hi>That it was not ſo before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was ever ſo in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> except in ſome extraordinary Caſes, where Ordination by Biſhops could not be had; as in the Caſe of the three <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Biſhops: but here the Caſe is altered, there being Biſhops ready to give Orders, ever ſince 1660; wherefore ſuch as have been Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Presbyters ſince that time, may be ſaid to do it in Contempt of their Authority in that Caſe; nor were thoſe that were Ordained before that time deprived of an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to take their Orders from the Hands of a Biſhop, there being ſome ſtill ready to confer them; and many in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Years did accept of thoſe Orders from Biſhops; which argues, that ſuch as did not refuſe it in Contempt, or for their Preferment, which was denyed to ſome, becauſe they had been Epiſcopally Ordained; but the main Argument may be taken from Dr. <hi>Beveridge</hi>'s Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>If any Man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch Cuſtom, neither the Churches of God:</hi> for ſearch all the Eccleſiaſtical Records, and you will find, that, except in caſe of great neceſſity, no Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath ever been accounted valid, but ſuch as hath been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by the Hands of a Biſhop; and if any did conteſt it, they have been branded as contentious Perſons.</p>
            <p>This Country-Miniſter therefore aſſumes too much to himſelf, to preſcribe to the Convocation in ſo material a Point, and urge Arguments for it, when the Commiſſioners were only to prepare Materials for the Convocation to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101060:20"/>of. But he pleads farther, <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>Quod fieri non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit factum valet: Though it ought not to be done, yet being done, it is valid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is denied, becauſe both thoſe Presbyters that gave it, and theſe who received it, were guilty of a Schiſm, as much then as now (for the Practice is ſtill continued) Epiſcopal Ordination, being ſtill to be had without any conſiderable difficulty. And the Author grants, that St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> (tho' pleading the Cauſe of Presbyters againſt Biſhops, yet) grants, that it was the ſole Prerogative and diſtinguiſhing Character of that Order <hi>(viz.)</hi> of Biſhops to Ordain: His words are, <hi>Quid enim non faciat Presbyter, quod facit Epiſcopus excepta Sola Ordinatione:</hi> And therefore the <hi>Salvo's</hi> which he makes for the ſake of ſome particular perſons, againſt the conſtant practice of the Univerſal Church, and particularly againſt the Law of the Land, cannot be excuſed from being a Plea for the preſent Schiſm; and the perpetuating thereof, ſuch Ordinations being ſtill practiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 12. He ſpeaks concerning Declarations and Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: the reſult whereof is, That he perſwades himſelf, (and I think he will not perſwade many others, beſides thoſe who already ſtand out) that what is generally underſtood by thoſe Subſcriptions and Declarations, ought to be more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed: For if it be generally ſo underſtood already, as he would have it, what need is there to have it more plainly expreſſed? <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the former, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Aſſent and Conſent is to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of the Common-Prayer; the latter <hi>(viz.)</hi> Subſcription to the Articles, is as to Articles of Peace and Concord, which, he ſays, is the Senſe of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> as he underſtands it (againſt <hi>Fiſher, p.</hi> 51. <hi>n.</hi> 2.) And without doubt that of Archbiſhop <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> (Schiſm guarded, <hi>S.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Chilingworth</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>Charity Maintained.</hi>) But yet, to maintain Schiſm and Contention, he forms a Caſe after this manner: <hi>Suppoſe a young Student</hi> (not a Diſſenter) <hi>thinks of entring into Holy
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101060:20"/>Orders; and conſidering what he is to do, meets firſt with the Declaration of his unfeigned aſſent and conſent to the uſe of all and every thing contained in and preſcribed by the Book of Common-Prayer; among which, he finds that the Apocrypha is to be read.</hi> (Of this Scruple we have ſpoken already.) <hi>Then he proceeds to the Pſalms, and comparing the two Tranſlations, finds ſome things inconſiſtent, and ſometimes the one to deny what the other affirms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And this Caſe hath been already ſeanned; but to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit nothing of his Objections, he adds, <hi>That this young Man finds in the two Tranſlations, ſome things inconſiſtent, and the one to deny what the other affirms; and being to uſe both, in the Desk, he reads,</hi> (as Pſal. 105.28.) They were not obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to his word; <hi>and in the Pulpit, with the Hebrew, and the new Tranſlations, he reads,</hi> They rebelled not againſt his word. To this I anſwer:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> There are many ſeeming Inconſiſtencies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions in that which he calls the Correct Tranſlation, (namely, from the <hi>Hebrew</hi>) which have occaſioned the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of divers Books, for the reconciling of them; and none but ſuch as are diſpoſed to Atheiſm, are offended at them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> This is ſuch a Blunder, as none but a Man wholly given to Contention, and is able to read the Reſolutions of Learned Men, could be guilty of; had he conſulted but Mr. <hi>P.</hi>'s <hi>Synopſis</hi> on the place, that the words <hi>LoMaru</hi> admits of an Interrogation, and that is a vehement affirmation, then the ſence of this Tranſlation, Did <hi>they not rebel?</hi> is as much as they <hi>did rebel</hi> againſt his word, which is the ſame with the other Tranſlation, (viz.) <hi>They were not obedient, or they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled against his word;</hi> thus the Hebrew Tranſlation agrees with the Septuagint: And of this among other inſtances, Mr. <hi>Poole</hi> gives one, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.26. we read, <hi>will they not ſtone us?</hi> when without the Interrogation, it would have been tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, <hi>They would not have ſtoned us;</hi> but the Septuagint al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101060:21"/>agrees well with the Hebrew Tranſlation, for the Verb plural may have reſpect to divers precedent Nouns, ſome whereof ſpeak <hi>de rebus &amp; ſignis,</hi> others <hi>de perſonis;</hi> Now the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> for the conviction of whom God executed the Plagues before ſpoken of, were not obedient to his word, and ſo both Tranſlations agree: Theſe and other Reſolutions are ſo clear, that I wonder how any Country-Miniſter, much leſs one of the City, ſhould at this time of the day, be ignorant of them; but none ſo blind as he that will not ſee; for it looks like a deſign in the Author, to foment Prejudices and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes in the Minds of young Men, to keep up a Schiſm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church. And ſo doth his next <hi>Plea,</hi> p. 14. againſt the uſe of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, whilſt he reſtrains the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory Sentences to one Article of the Creed, which is to be referred to the whole, for ſo ſays the Preface, <hi>This is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I think it not neceſſary to Salvation, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man ſhould believe that Article of the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from the Father to the Son, ſeeing there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Articles in the Creed called the Apoſtles, as we receive it now, which in the moſt Primitive Times, were not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in that Creed; for which conſult <hi>Voſſius, Armagh,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Pearſon,</hi> the late Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> and therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive that thoſe Greek Churches were Hereticks, and in a ſtate of Damnation, that held not the <hi>Filioque:</hi> And to this purpoſe the Letter makes his ſecond Quere, <hi>Whether this be a fundamental Article of the Faith, which except a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves he cannot be ſaved?</hi> Seeing as he grants it is not made neceſſary by <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf, nor was originally either in the <hi>Nicene</hi> (truly ſo called,) or <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed; <hi>Nor is it ſo thought by our Church,</hi> (ſays the Letter) <hi>which receiving the four first General Councils, agrees with that of</hi> Epheſus, (which is the third) <hi>which made a peremptory Decree against all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to be made thereafter to the Creed,</hi> Concil. Epheſ. Part 3. Art. 6. (Which ſhews that ſome Additions had been
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101060:21"/>formerly made,) <hi>From whence</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it follows, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe was then accounted neceſſary to be believed, but what was contained in the</hi> Nicene: And ſo the Damnatory Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces not appearing to be the Addition of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting any particular Article, but what is fundamental and neceſſary to Salvation; in the whole, the young Man, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any thing that the Letter ſaith, may Subſcribe the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed with the Damnatory Sentences, which are applicable only to ſuch as obſtinately deny the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Articles of the Chriſtian Faith contained in that Creed. And I deſire the Author of this Objection to conſider, what occaſion it hath given to the <hi>Antitrinitarians</hi> to proclaim their Blaſphemies againſt the Bleſſed Trinity, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the Chriſtian Religion; for a late Writer ſays, <hi>That</hi> Athanaſius <hi>was drunk when he wrote that Creed; That it is ſetled by a Tyrannical Dominion, and is a Superſtition or Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rather than true Religion; That the Follies and Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons charged on the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, are neither for Number, Conſequence or Greatneſs, comparable to thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the</hi> Athanaſian <hi>Creed; And that the Trinity hath the ſame foundation with Tranſubſtantiation, and we muſt admit both or neither.</hi> This Opinion of the <hi>Socinians</hi> hath been ſo confuted by our late Divines, that I ſhall not repeat their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments; ſo apt are our Adverſaries, of all ſorts, to improve the Objections of Diſſenters into very dangerous and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Errors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 15. This Country-Miniſter hath a very modeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt in behalf of himſelf and the Diſſenters, <hi>viz. That Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery may be reſtored to its ancient Priviledge, and permitted to ſhare in all Acts belonging to their Station.</hi> What Acts thoſe are, he ſufficiently intimates, but doth not enumerate; they muſt ſhare in the Juriſdiction and Adminiſtration of Diſcipline; in the iſſuing forth of Excommunications, and in the power of Conferring Orders; and this, forſooth, for the honour of the Biſhops to take off whatever they may ſuffer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101060:22"/>by Miſgovernment; and I ſuppoſe they would quickly draw too much of that Odium upon themſelves: Wherefore as he doth, ſo ſhall I leave theſe things to the mature conſideration of the Convocation; and how likely it is that the Church would not be the worſe for theſe Alterations.</p>
            <p>But concerning this, he raiſeth two Objections: the firſt is, <hi>Where are they that would come in upon theſe Conceſſions and Alterations?</hi> And, <hi>2dly,</hi> if they do come in, what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage this will be to the Church? To the firſt he ſays, 'tis but to try; and I ſay, whatever the Church can grant, and not be the worſe for it, hath been already tried, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rejected, though the Conceſſions were more than the Convocation can now with prudence and ſafety grant them; for theſe will not ſtifle their clamours againſt the Church, who have publickly declared, that they expect greater things: <hi>But in juſtice and integrity,</hi> ſays the Letter, <hi>theſe things ought to be granted; for it was promiſed by their Biſhops,</hi> (viz.) <hi>that they wanted not due tenderneſs towards Diſſenters, but were willing to come to ſuch a temper as ſhould be thought fit when that matter ſhould be conſidered and ſetled in Parliament and Convocation.</hi> But as he ſays they promiſed it when it was not in their power, and now (the more is the pity) it is not in their power to perform it; but they promiſed no more than was fit to be granted <hi>(i. e.)</hi> upon great and important Reaſons, nor more than what ſhould be thought fit by a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Convocation, to which it is ſtill referred.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> He inquires what benefit this will be to the Church? To which I anſwer, None at all; if, as he ſays, when kept out they are Enemies, and when let in they will be no Friends: but when they have more power and opportunity, they may do more miſchief. <hi>S. M. E. C. T. Y. M. N. W. S.</hi> were in the Church in 1641, and did it more hurt than thoſe that were kept out; and there are ſtill ſuch among us, as are not of us, whoſe Names would make up as terrible a word, as that of <hi>Smectymnuus;</hi> but I forbear to call Names.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101060:22"/>
            <p>His third General is, <hi>That there are ſuch things in our Church, as may be altered for the better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thus ſome Men have attempted to mend the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat; but finding they could not do that, they reſolved to lay it aſide: And many an unskilful Architect hath under taken to repair a good old Fabrick, and make it better; but by pulling down Beam after Beam, and after a leſſer Stone a greater, till the whole Fabrick hath been like to fall; and then (what perhaps was deſigned at firſt) he perſwades the Owners, that there is a neceſſity wholly to deſtroy the old, and erect a new one upon better foundations: And thus the Country-Miniſter thinks he hath cleared the Point, and may come in for a ſhare in the imployment and benefit. And firſt he ingageth to make eaſie and ſhort work of it, and would not have his Country-Brethren to be obliged to their daily labour in the Service of the Church, but to be left free to attend it how and when they pleaſe, to perform one part of the Service at one time, and another at another, and to be left to their own diſcretion, and not tied up to Forms, and to do what is commanded them. Thus he pleads for himſelf and fellow-labourers, whom he thinks fit to ſhare with the Maſter-builders; and to that end he thus miſ-repreſents them, <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>That they are ready to impoſe ſuch burthens on others, as they will not touch with themſelves; That they only walk from a warm Houſe to a Cathedral, and for half an hour turn over a Service-book, hear a Sermon, and return to a warm Room and good Fare, and know not what it is to do the Service of a Cure perhaps all their life.</hi> This would be very edifying Doctrine in a Conventicle, but not ſo acceptable, when a Country-Miniſter ſhall preach it to a Convocation, which conſiſts of the ſelect Clergy of the Land, who are, for the moſt part, obliged to the Service of God in Cathedrals, or in their own Churches; and moreover, to all thoſe Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which the Country-Miniſter is bound to do: And which is as difficult a work, as any of the other, to Overſee thoſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101060:23"/>Labourers, leaſt they do more hurt than good by their Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Ignorance, or Immorality; for too many ſuch there be, who, if they were kept to their daily duty, might be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from many inconveniencies, which are more prejudicial to their Lives, than the appointed Service of God would be. And doubtleſs the Convocation will not be of the Country-Miniſter's mind, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>That he ſhould be left to his diſcretion to read one part of the Service one day, and another another; and in the Afternoon to leave out the firſt Leſſon, or the like; leaving out on</hi> Sunday <hi>the Communion-Service, and ſhortning the Liturgy at the Lord's-Prayer.</hi> For which he gives this reaſon, <hi>That it was compoſed peculiarly with reſpect to a State of Perſecution:</hi> For which cauſe it ought rather to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued; for he asks the Queſtion, <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>Are we without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? and if not, have we leſs danger to fear now, when we are divided, than when united?</hi> But why muſt the Communion-Service be left out, when the Primitive Church did commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate at their daily Aſſemblies? And it is the Peoples fault that the Communion is not Adminiſtred every <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Pariſh-Churches, as well as in the Cathedrals; ſo that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that Service minds the People of their backwardneſs to partake of ſo great a Bleſſing, and both minds and prepares them for it.</p>
            <p>But I ſee not to what end theſe Offices ſhould be ſhortned, except it be to yield to the Country-Miniſter's extemporary Prayers, and tedious Sermons; which if left to his diſcretion, would doubtleſs be the conſequence. And his deſire, <hi>That the firſt Leſſon, or the like, may be left out in the Afternoon, that Men may fodder their Cattel; when, I ſuppoſe, the turning of the Afternoons Sermon into Catechizing, may better anſwer that end, and be more profitable to the People, both young and old; and it is more agreeable to Order; and this courſe would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hamper their Conſciences, nor expoſe them to the raſh Cenſures of thoſe whom he calls their not over-laborious Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren:</hi> Which Epithet ſome ſuch Country-Miniſters as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101060:23"/>may deſerve; <hi>p.</hi> 19. he would have <hi>ſome of the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſent down to ſome Country-Pariſhes, to eaſe the poor Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, by reading Prayers and Preaching,</hi> &amp;c. As if the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Convocation never did perform the intire Service of the Church in Praying and Preaching.</p>
            <p>The Country-Miniſter might conſider, that a great part of them have travelled, ſome a hundred, ſome near two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miles, to meet in Convocation, to conſult for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefit of the Clergy, and ſit ſometime near the whole day in a cold place, in the depth of Winter: And ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Miniſters, now of the Convocation, do now ſee in what great eaſe and plenty the City-Miniſters live, who have their Readers and Lecturers, and frequent Supplies, and ſometimes tarry in the Veſtry till Prayers be ended, and have great Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities in the Church, beſides their rich Pariſhes in the City.</p>
            <p>Having pleaded for the ſhortning of the Liturgy, he pleads, <hi>p.</hi> 22. for the prolonging of it, by adding an Office to receive Penitents after an Apoſtacy, and in caſe of notorious Scandal: this may concern the Country-Miniſter. 2. For receiving perſons Abſolved after Excommunication: this, as he deſires, is left to the diſcretion of the Prieſt that Officiates. 3. An Office for the Priſoners, which is provided for by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, who generally appoint able Men for that charitable Office. So that all this notwithſtanding, he concludes in the words of Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> &amp;c. concerning the Liturgy, as it ſtood before the 600 Amendments in 1661. <hi>That the Book of Common-Prayer is the moſt compleat, perfect and exact Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy in the Chriſtian World, and ſuch as a Godly Man may with a good Conſcience uſe, and not only lawfully, but comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly joyn in.</hi> Wherefore it having already received ſo many Amendments, there ſhould be ſome important Reaſons given why it ſhould admit of more, for his May-be's are no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments: It may-be ſome things are obſcure, and too doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully expreſs'd; It may be in its Phraſeology liable to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>application; It may be too fanciful: And all theſe May-be's,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101060:24"/>may not be, if the moſt exceptionable Expreſſions in the whole Liturgy be allowed (as the Preface to it ſays) ſuch juſt and favourable conſtruction, as in common equity ought to be allowed to all humane Writings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 23. Our Author comes to enquire more nicely into it, but whether more wiſely let the Reader judge: He inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth firſt in what he thinks obſcure: As in the Prayer for the Clergy: <hi>Who alone workeſt great Marvels, ſend down,</hi> &amp;c. of which, Who dares deny, ſaith Dr. <hi>Comber,</hi> that the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance granted to the Miniſters for the converſion of ſinners are as marvellous, as was the Creation of Light out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or the Reſurrection from the Dead: ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.19. So in the Collect for <hi>Trinity Sunday, Who hath given us Grace in the Power of the Divine Majeſty, to Worſhip the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> This is not obſcure to any that acknowledgeth the Trinity, which is to be worſhipped in the Unity of Divine Majeſty: As when in the Litany we pray, <hi>O holy bleſſed and glorious Trinity, three Perſons and one God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Preface at the Communion for <hi>Trinity Sunday,</hi> that which we believe of the Glory of the Father, the ſame we believe of the Glory of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difference or inequality, <hi>(viz.)</hi> as to the Godhead, Chriſt having ſaid, <hi>I and my Father are one:</hi> And the Church in all Ages hath profeſſed the ſame belief in the Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and aſcribes the ſame Glory to each of them in the <hi>Treſagion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Prayer before the Communion: <hi>That our ſinful Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies may be made clean by his Body, and our Souls waſhed through his moſt precious Blood: (i.e.)</hi> that both our Souls and Bodies may receive all the benefits of his Death and Paſſion.</p>
            <p>In the Office of Baptiſm: <hi>By the Baptiſm of thy well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son in the River</hi> Jordan, <hi>didſt ſanstifie Water: (i. e.)</hi> didſt appoint and conſecrate the Element of Water, to be the outward ſign of the Grace conferred in that Sacrament by the Blood and Merits of Chriſt. In the Office of Matrimony:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101060:24"/>
               <hi>With my Body I thee Worſhip:</hi> Which ſignifies a civil Reſpect and Honour, and is more ſignificant than what they would exchange it for, <hi>(viz.)</hi> I give thee Power over my Body. In that of Burial: <hi>Foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed Almighty God to take to himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. By which no more is meant, than what, as ſome underſtand, the Scripture ſays: <hi>The Spirit returns to God that gave it:</hi> or if it ſuppoſeth Diſcipline; ſo it expreſſeth Charity, where Diſcipline hath not excluded them from the Communion of the Church, that we hope they reſt with God. So in the Collect for <hi>Eaſter-Sunday,</hi> where the Preface and the Petition want a better Connexion: The Preface and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion are thus: <hi>That as God by Chriſt hath opened to us the Gate of everlaſting Life, ſo he would (prepare us for that life) putting into our Hearts good Deſires, by his ſpecial Grace pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting us, and by his continual help we may bring the ſame to good effect.</hi> So the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Eaſter, &amp;c.</hi> the Preface is, <hi>Almighty God who haſt given thy only Son to die for our Sins, and to riſe for our Juſtification:</hi> The Connexion is: <hi>Grant us ſo to die unto ſin,</hi> (which is the ſenſe of) to put away the leaven of Malice, that we may ſerve thee in pureneſs of living and truth, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> we may live unto God. 2. He inſtanceth in ſome things liable to miſapplication; as in the Viſitation of the Sick: <hi>By his Authority committed to me, I abſolve thee; which the Prieſt having prayed God to do, he applieth in</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine domini, in the Name of the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity committed to me as God's Miniſter, I abſolve thee, <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.23. And the Anſwer in the Catechiſm: <hi>The Body and Bloud of Christ, which are verily and indeed taken and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Faithful in the Lord's Supper:</hi> (i. e.) in a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but real manner by the faithful Communicants; for there is ſufficient caution given againſt the Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. So in the Exhortation for warning of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: <hi>Becauſe it is requiſite no Man ſhould come to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion, but with a full truſt in God's Mercy, and with a quiet Conſcience:</hi> For if St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, we may not partake
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101060:25"/>of common things with a doubting Conſcience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. much leſs of ſpiritual: And when Men conſult the Lawyers for their Eſtates, and Phyſitians for their Bodies, why ſhould they not conſult the Miniſters for their Souls? Such again are thoſe Collects which too much incline to the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Phraſe, laying the force of temptation, and Man's liableneſs to ſin, upon the frailty, and not the corruption of our Nature; as the firſt and 24th <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Trinity:</hi> what they mean by frailty, that firſt Collect explains, to be ſuch, as that without God we can do no good thing, which is the great corruption of our Nature; and no Doctrine concerning the corruption of Nature is more plain, than that in our Articles. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Some Collects, he ſays, <hi>are too fanciful, and ſavour of the Breviary, as thoſe of St.</hi> Luke, <hi>St.</hi> John, Simon <hi>and</hi> Jude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whatever in the Breviaries are taken out of the Scripture, or Authentick and Ancient Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, is not therefore to be rejected; and that St. <hi>Luke</hi> was that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Phyſitian mentioned <hi>Col.</hi> 4.14. is the conſtant aſſertion of all Interpreters, and the expreſs words of the Scripture; therefore no Legend. Of theſe he ſays, <hi>That in a ſort they need amendment:</hi> And ſo doth the Judgment of this nice En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirer, who, I fear, hath loſt his <hi>Rationale,</hi> which he might eaſily ſupply from Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s, or Biſhop <hi>Sparrow</hi>'s Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. A Man would think this Writer to have been hired to betray the Cauſe of the Diſſenters, by his weak and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Arguments for its defence: and a great conviction it will be to many, that there need no Alterations to be made, when their prime Advocate inſiſts on ſuch Inſtances as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him vain and ridiculous. Many things he would add to the Office of Confirmation: <hi>viz.</hi> An Exhortation on the <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> before, and a Diſcourſe about the Nature, Uſe, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of it; and a ſerious Exhortation after it, with ſome Inlargements of the Collects; by all which he provides to bring down the Biſhops to more labour than he would have any Country-Miniſter to perform, conſidering what other
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101060:25"/>Offices they uſually perform at the ſame time <hi>(viz.)</hi> Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Holy Sacraments, Ordination of Prieſts and Deacons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were eaſie, ſaith our Author, to be copious on this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But he hath ſaid enough, by chuſing out ſuch inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are beyond all exceptions for their ſignificancy, and ſelf-evidence; ſo that the very reading of them, is a ſufficient Confutation of this Author's Cavils, and a Juſtification of them from his frivolous Accuſations; which not being very grateful to him (as he confeſſeth) will be very offenſive to others.</p>
            <p>Yet (ſo importune are ſome ſort of Men) he will not leave the point ſo, but will ſhew, that this is a fit ſeaſon for ſuch Alterations) when he hath not ſhewn the leaſt cauſe, much leſs any neceſſity for making of them; but firſt he lays the blame on ſome that are in the Convocation, that ſhould tell him, This is not a ſeaſon: which he would diſprove by this Queſtion: <hi>Is there any thing can make that not to be ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which is always a Duty:</hi> As if it were alway a Duty, to make needleſs Alterations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is <hi>there any Seaſon in which we are not as much as in us lieth, to ſeek Peace and enſue it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Peace of the Church is more to be valued, than of thoſe who diſquiet themſelves and others in vain. Was it a Seaſon for the Repreſentatives of our Church to declare, when they were not in a condition, They wanted not a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs toward Diſſenters? And is it not their Seaſon when they are in a condition? (which I heartily wiſh they were, even for the Diſſenters ſake) becauſe he hath ſaid, He doubts not but they would agree to the Alterations that are deſired.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe, ſays he, there were never a Diſſenter in the Land; I ſay, we might have a happier and fitter Seaſon, when there would be none that watch for our haltings, and ſeek oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to accuſe us from our own Conceſſions, and will reject them with ſcorn and contempt; and ſo our Liturgy and Worſhip, which (the Letter ſays) was compleat and perfect before, be expoſed as not only infirm, but ſo corrupt, that it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101060:26"/>needed Alterations; and that for very ſhame the Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thought it neceſſary to make them. But our Author find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his arguings to be loſt, as in <hi>p</hi> 28. he betakes himſelf to a ſham-plot againſt thoſe that are not for Alterations, as if becauſe they ſaid, or rather he for them, That they were not ſeaſonable: they had ſaid, the Parliament was illegal, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment precarious, and the Laws no Laws, it becomes not a Country-Miniſter to be a Miniſter of Satan, in falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Brethren, who have all owned the preſent Authority and Laws, and he that blames the want of Connexion in our Collects, ſhould have been more cautious, then firſt to raiſe an Objection of his own, and then infer from it ſuch impertinent concluſions as may be miſchievous to others. But what think you, ſays he, if this Government ſink? I think our cauſleſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions will be one of the greateſt cauſes: Who ſunk the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment under the Royal Martyr? Who had well nigh ſunk it a ſecond time under the late King? to whom ſuch multitude of Diſſenters addreſſed Thanks for Suſpending the Laws, and promiſed to obey him without reſerve: we have had experience enough who they were that could, after all their Pleas for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, part with their Conſciences to ſave their Lives, though with the loſs of their Religion, Laws, and Liberty; ſo as their Brethren might periſh a little before them. When therefore he would perſwade us, that we may have a new Law for the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Eſtabliſhment; I think no Man will be perſwaded to run ſuch a riſque; for having many good Laws already for our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Worſhip, we may conclude, that as to certainty the old are better. Having thus treated the Members of the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, he takes his Farewel of them, leaving them to their Couch and Conſideration; intimating, that they are all become mighty Politicians, or Tools for them that are ſo. Who have been made and uſed as Tools by the late unhappy Politicians is as evident as any matter of fact can be, and I wiſh I could leave this Country-Miniſter well in his Wits, to conſider whether he be not uſed as a Tool to deſtroy the Eſtabliſhed Church, by ſome who think themſelves mighty Politicians.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:101060:26"/>
            <head>Some <hi>REMARKS on a</hi> LETTER from a Member of the <hi>Convocation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NO ſooner had I finiſhed my Remarks on the Letter of <hi>the Country Miniſter to a Member of the Convocation,</hi> but I were encounter'd with another from <hi>a Member of the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Friend;</hi> in which I feared my Opinion would have been oppugned, not only by a greater Authority, but by ſharper Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than any I had yet met with: But having viewed his Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, I found that they were flouriſhed and glittered with a Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical ſtyle, yet they wanted that Logical ſtrength that might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them. This encouraged me to take my Pen in hand again, and to enter the Liſt againſt this Maſter of the Aſſembly; for I conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that though his Weapons were keen, yet the Arm that wielded them was but weak, and it was no great danger to wreſt them out of his hands, and imploy them againſt himſelf: His great flouriſh was, <hi>A Neceſſity, an abſolute Neceſſity of yielding to many Alterations in our Eſtabliſhed Worſhip.</hi> This I thought might prove <hi>durum telum;</hi> for, <hi>Neceſſity hath no Law,</hi> eſpecially when it is Abſolute; then, like the Abſolute power, it bears down all before it: This lookt ſomewhat formidably; for I conſidered that Neceſſity had deſtroyed many great and good Men. It was ſaid of that great Hero, the Earl of <hi>Strafford, Illum non tulit Lex verum neceſſitas non habens Legem;</hi> And of a greater than he we have a Law <hi>(viz.)</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> making, and by that Law, <hi>Oportet mori,</hi> to dye, and dye he did, becauſe it was expedient alſo for the People.</p>
            <p>But that there was an Abſolute neceſſity that <hi>Judas</hi> ſhould betray his Maſter; I can no more believe, than that there is a Neceſſity, That he who is a Member of the Church of Chriſt, and hath fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly, eaten of her Bread, and born the Bag too, ſhould lift up his heels and kick at her. I conſidered therefore what kind of Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty this might be, for our Opponent grants, there is no neceſſity in reſpect of the Church her ſelf, that ſhe ſhould make Alterations: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſaith he, <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>nothing is more dangerous to Religion, than frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make Alterations.</hi> 2. Becauſe an unſteadineſs, though in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials only, which are always alterable, may become an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the whole, the Multitude not being able to judge
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101060:27"/>what is Circumſtantial, and what is Eſſential in our Worſhip; what is in the Power of the Church to alter, and what is not; and are apt to call every Alteration, though in things indifferent, and by varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of times made totally inſignificant, to be a change of Religion it ſelf, and ſo concluding that we have no firm bottom, become Apoſtates from us to Popery or Atheiſm. And therefore he thinks the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be juſtified, that it hath not been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on every demand of the Diſſenters to unhinge thoſe of her Communion, but hath to the utmoſt reſiſted all Alterations, hoping by other leſs dangerous Methods to heal the Diviſions that are among us. By this I perceived the Abſolute neceſſity would not much affect the Church; yet I conſidered farther, whether there were an Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity from any Precept that did oblige the Church to make Alterations in the external Parts or Rites of Worſhip; and I found ſhe had a Power by Precept to ſee that all things be done decently, and according to her Order and Appointment; and another Precept, <hi>That the People ſhould Obey thoſe that had the Rule over them.</hi> And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the moſt Primitive Church, of which we read <hi>Acts</hi> 2.45. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued daily with one accord in the Temple, and in the Apoſtle's Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayer:</hi> Nor would St. <hi>Paul</hi> endure any Contention about Circumſtantials, contrary to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. Nor can I ſee this Abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in the things that are to be altered, becauſe they are confeſſed to be in their own nature indifferent; and when they fall under a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of thoſe whoſe proper work it is to injoyn them, we cannot without Diſobedience to our lawful Governors, reject them. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can this Neceſſity affect the Perſons for whoſe ſake the Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are deſired; becauſe if there be nothing ſinful in our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is ſinful to ſeparate from it; beſides, the Diſſenters would take it ill of any Man that ſhould ſay they cannot be ſaved in that way of Worſhip which they have choſen for themſelves; and then there is no Abſolute neceſſity for the Church to alter her Conſtitutions to gain them to her Communion: In a Church where Salvation is to be had, we ought to abide, notwithſtanding ſome inconvenient cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, whoſe Amendment is deſirable. Though there were great Diſputes in the Primitive Church about the Place of Worſhip, Circumciſion, and Meats and Days, yet was there no Separation: And the conſtant Voice of the Church was, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let ancient Cuſtoms prevail.</hi> But here Abſolute neceſſity is urged for Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, becauſe all other means have been tried, and prove ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to heal our Diviſions. To which I Anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:101060:27"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Acts for Uniformity were much more effectual than any Alterations that the Church can juſtly make will be, ſeeing the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters have declared they will not be ſatisfied with the Alterations of our Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but expect greater matters than the Church can grant. 2. Experience ſhews, that they will not acquieſce in ſuch Alterations as may be granted. 3. Becauſe it was not for want of ſucceſs, that Toleration was granted againſt the Act for Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; but becauſe it was too ſucceſsful, and the Common Enemies of our Church perceiving the good effects of that Act, which had well nigh reduced the whole Nation to an Uniformity, with their joynt Intereſt procured a Toleration; and it needs no proof, That if the Act for Uniformity hath made one Diſſenter, Toleration and Alterations have made hundreds; ſo that as there is no <hi>Neceſſitas praecepti,</hi> neither is there <hi>Neceſſitas med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> to obtain the Ends which this Author propoſeth.</p>
            <p>And thus we have put off the firſt blow of this Abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the ſecond will be as eaſily warded; for if there be no Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity to make any Alterations, then 'tis not abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that we ſhould make them now: For there is no neceſſity that we ſhould expoſe our ſelves to that reproach, which is endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be fixed on ſome of us, of being Eccleſiaſtical Tinkers, who undertaking to mend one hole, do uſually make two or three. We have, by ſtanding our ground, put to flight one formidable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and is there an Abſolute neceſſity, that by giving ground, we ſhould bring our ſelves under the Power of another? And ſuch an Enemy, as our Author ſays, did (once and therefore may be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of doing it again) take ſhelter in the Camp of out Common Enemy, and joyned with the Papiſts againſt us, endangering the Church and State to utter turn, <hi>p.</hi> 3. This methinks ſhould blunt the edge of his Abſolute neceſſity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 3. The Author makes the excepted Paſſages in our Liturgy, and the Ceremonies in our Worſhip, the whole Origine of our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. As if the whole blame lay on the Church, whereof be is an Eminent Miniſter; As if the Ignorance of ſome Diſſenters, and the intereſt and Obſtinacy or others that know more, were in no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner culpable; no, not though they rail at our Ceremonies as Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, and our Biſhops as Antichriſtian and Tyrannical; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn not our Liturgy only, but our Uſe of our Lord's-Prayer. And our Author, contrary to his hounden Duty, adminiſters incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſome of theſe, while he reflection the Penal Laws and Church-cenſures, which, he ſays, <hi>have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101060:28"/>the Miſchiefs which they endeavoured to remove; and that they were executed with an unjuſtifiable Severity:</hi> Though if they had been legally executed againſt the Papiſt, and ſuch Diſſenters as joyned with them, it might have prevented that greater Severity, which was exerciſed againſt ſome whole Colledges, and the Seven Famous Biſhops, who were ſent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> in order to their (and in them, to the) deſtruction of our Religion, Laws, and Liberties, which by their Conſtancy they preſerved to us, however apt we are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe them, and deal with them as in Forty Two, they were dealt with by the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> and Diſſenters Malice. What tho' there be ſome few that are really, but cauſleſly offended at our Ceremonies, muſt we for their ſakes give offence to the Church of God; we have found concerning the greateſt part of the Diſſenters, that it is not their <hi>Cannot,</hi> but their <hi>Will not</hi> that keeps them from our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and when their Intereſt and Advantage requires it, they can Conform; And what neceſſity is there, that for the ſake of a few ignorant, or peeviſh, and unſatisfiable perſons, that will not be pleaſed with all that we can do, we ſhould confirm them in their obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, by yielding and complying with their humors? Who were not offended at the excepted paſſages of our Liturgy and Ceremonies onely, but at Epiſcopacy, at our Doctrine, at the whole Liturgy, and even at our Lord's Prayer, which they diſuſed.</p>
            <p>The next for which he ſays there was a preſſing neceſſity, is the late Act for Toleration, for which he gives theſe Reaſons: 1. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Diſſenters were driven to take ſhelter in the Camp of our common Enemy, and joyn with the Papiſts:</hi> Or rather, the Papiſts by the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration ſheltred themſelves under the Diſſenters: However, it is a good confeſſion of this Author, and ſhews, that they who ſtrained at a Gnat could ſwallow Camels: And though one Parliament paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an Act for Toleration, yet another gave ſuch Arguments againſt it, as are not yet, nor, I believe, can be anſwered; which are late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Printed in a Tract entituled, <hi>An Anſwer to the Letter for Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, p.</hi> 28. Nor is it evident, that by the Act for Toleration, the Diſſenters are put on as good a bottom of Legal Right, as the Church is; for it is well known, by what means, and for what end a Toleration hath been more than once obtained, which <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do teſtifie; and Toleration implies ſomewhat more culpable than the Eſtabliſhed Government, and never deſerved the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, having been often rejected. And whereas he deſires a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from him that can give it, <hi>Why we ſhould not abate a few excepted paſſages in our Liturgy, and two or three Ceremonies?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:101060:28"/>
            <p>I <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe, as hath been often ſaid, the giving up of theſe will give the Diſſenters no ſatisfaction; and, becauſe the Remedy hath been worſe than the Diſeaſe, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the retaining of our Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and excepted paſſages, never cauſed ſo much Impiety, ſo many Sects and Errors, as the laying them aſide hath done; the Twenty Years War from 40 to 60, and the Thirty Years Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties laſt paſt, had other Cauſes than what he (very unbecoming a Member of the Church, and, as he calls himſelf, one of the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation) terms Trifles, and <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>A Bone of Contention:</hi> The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſhews what cauſed that War, the deſtruction of Epiſcopacy Root and Branch, the ſetting up of Presbytery, the dividing of the Revenues of the Church among themſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When therefore he calls that unreaſonable Rigor, which enjoyned Uniformity in our Worſhip; he reflects on the Act for Uniformity, and the Canons of the Church, to which he hath ſubſcribed; ſo that he and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are more like to loſe their Reputation with the People, tho' he would caſt all the Odium upon us, whom he expects and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make to be abhorred of the Nation as the Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of its Peace, and be treated accordingly in every Pariſh where we live. <hi>Did we contend againſt the Arrians,</hi> ſays he, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>we would not yield them a Letter to end the whole Controverſie?</hi> And are not the <hi>Arrians</hi> coming in, when the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed is ſo ridicul'd, as hath been ſhewn? And did not the Church in St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s time, contend as much againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who could plead for themſelves, as this Author doth for the Diſſenters? What Article of Faith? What ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary requiſite of our Worſhip is it in which any Alterations are intended? This St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> granted, <hi>Nobiſcum eſtis in Evangelio in Sacramentis idem cantatis Hallelujah, ſed hoc ſolo nomine;</hi> For this only cauſe that they made Diviſions and Separations in and from the Church, he excluded them, not only from the Church, but from Salvation; and it is obſervable, that the <hi>Arrians</hi> did not only come in among the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> but theſe joyned with the <hi>Arrians</hi> againſt the Church; how confidently ſoever therefore he would aſſure us, that the intended Alterations are only in things indifferent; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take his word for it, for many things have been well intended, the conſequences whereof have proved fatal and deſtructive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 8. <hi>Our Saviour</hi> (he ſays) <hi>preſcribed not the particular Rites and Conſtitutions which the Church made uſe of:</hi> Very true; but when the Church preſcribed the Uſe of them, that all things, in the Publick Worſhip might be done decently, and in order, they were judged contentious Perſons that did not conform to them: and therefore I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101060:29"/>agree with him, that as long as thoſe Forms of Prayer uſed in our Church, and thoſe Rites and Conſtitutions which are received, do anſwer the Ends of their firſt Eſtabliſhment, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Honour of God, and Edification of the People, they ought with conſtancy alway to be retained: And in what Aſſembly, not only of the Sectaries, but of any Reformed Church in the World, either for purity of Doctrine, fervency in Devotion, and decency in Worſhip, is the Honour of God, and the Edification of the People better provided for, than in the approved Aſſemblies of the Church. But in this which follows, I think, no ſober Perſon can agree with him: (viz.) <hi>That when either the infirmity or wickedneſs of Men makes any Alterations, and adminiſter to Schiſm and Diviſion,</hi> then he ſays, <hi>there ariſeth a reaſon altogether as ſtrong for their Alteration, as there was for their Inſtitution:</hi> That is, we muſt alter a godly and well eſtabliſhed Worſhip, as oft as the wickedneſs of Men requires it: And how ſuch an Eſtabliſhed Worſhip ſhould become miſchievous, and ſo bring on the Church an Obligation (which without guilt cannot be reſiſted,) to make a change, is a very bold ſaying: For, Suppoſe the Papiſts arguing thus againſt the Scripture, or againſt our Liturgy, that it had occaſioned many miſchievous Schiſms and Errors, were it a ſtrong Argument for us to lay them aſide? And ſhould we be guilty if we did not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 9. He deſcends to particulars: And concerning the Croſs, <hi>p.</hi> 10. he ſays: <hi>I think we have an Obligation upon us, not to be reſiſted from abſolute neceſſity of the thing, either totally to lay this Ceremony aſide, or make ſuch Abatements as may allay our Heats of Contention, and Miſchiefs of Separation as have been cauſed thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If I were of the Judgment of this Convocation Man, I would not tarry any longer in the Communion of that Church, which enjoyns the Uſe of the Croſs, tho' I were a Dean or Arch-Deacon. But how comes this Man to be more ſcrupulous than Mr. <hi>Baxter?</hi> who ſays, <hi>He will not condemn Ancients or Moderns that uſe it, nor make any diſturbance about it in the Church:</hi> His Opinion is grounded <hi>on an unwary Expreſſion,</hi> as he calls it, in the Canons: <hi>That by it the Perſon Baptized is dedicated to the Service of Jeſus Christ; and ſo attributes a Sacramental effect to it, which belongs only to Baptiſm.</hi> Sure this Perſon did never conſider, that the Church hath declared that Sacrament ſufficiently adminiſtred where the Croſs is omitted; and had he conſidered the definition of a Sacrament in the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, he might perceive, that no part of that definition agrees with the Croſs to make it Sacramental; and when we ſee that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:101060:29"/>for laying aſide the Croſs, have been improved to the layin aſide of Baptiſm, let the Author conſider where the guilt doth lie.</p>
            <p>As to the Surplice, <hi>p.</hi> 11. he ſays, <hi>Nothing is more unreaſonable than the Cavils againſt it; yet he would have it totally laid aſide, and another Habit appointed:</hi> And if that other ſhould be laid aſide, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he there gives, we might as eaſily fit a Garment for the Moon, as one that ſhould pleaſe all Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 11. <hi>Kneeling at the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, is the last Conſtitution of the Church,</hi> that he ſays, <hi>he ſhould willingly part with:</hi> The reſt, it ſeems, may go with his good will; and ſo may this alſo, by what follows: <hi>(viz.) I can ſee no reaſon that ſavours either of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Temper or Charity, why to communicate ſtanding, may not be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to weak and ſcrupulous Perſons:</hi> He can, it ſeems, ſee a reaſon, why the ſcrupulous Perſon ſhould forbear that bleſſed Sacrament, for fear of a fit and preſcribed Ceremony; but can ſee none, why the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould not be adminiſtred to them in their own way. I would ask him, Is it not fit when we pray with the Miniſter as we ought to do, <hi>that the Body of our Lord Jeſus Christ, which was given for thee, preſerve thy Body and Soul to everlaſting life,</hi> to kneel? Or is it decent one ſhould ſtand, and another kneel? And is not Obedience in ſuch things, better than ſacrificing to our own humours, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king confuſion in ſo ſolemn an Ordinance? Whether the ancient Communicants did ſtand or kneel, they did in obedience to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church; and ſo ought we. Hear Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in this caſe: <hi>If it be lawful to take a Pardon from the King upon our knees, I know not what can make it unlawful, to take a ſealed Pardon from Chriſt upon our knees,</hi> See <hi>Chriſtian Direct.</hi> p. 616. <hi>And as for kneeling at the Sacrament, ſince the Rubrick, my Judgment was ever for it: God having made ſome Geſture neceſſary, and confined us to none, but left it to humane determination: I ſhall ſubmit to Magiſtrates in their proper work. I am not ſure, Chriſt intended his Example as obligatory; but I am ſure he hath commanded me Obedience and Peace.</hi> p. 411. of the Five Diſputations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 12. <hi>The Liturgy,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>is the beſt that ever was uſed in any Chriſtian Church:</hi> If then we cannot joyn with our Church therein, we cannot joyn with any Chriſtian Church: Yet <hi>p.</hi> 13. he thinks it <hi>abſolutely neceſſary, not only that it be altered now, but every thirty Years.</hi> And what example doth he ſet before us, but the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, which have ſeveral Liturgies; becauſe they conſiſt of ſeveral National Governments: but from the beginning of the Reformation, under <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. was the firſt Law for an uniform Liturgy; And ſhall we take example from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or from our Reformers? It was indeed neceſſary, that it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in thoſe days, becauſe all Popiſh Superſtitions could not be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101060:30"/>caſt off at once. He tell us, <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>Of many Alterations formerly made, and would fain know a reaſon why we ſhould not make more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe there is not ſuch reaſon, as was to reform the Liturgies in the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. when there was Criſme, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the Dead, and ſuch other things, which <hi>Calvin</hi> called, <hi>Tolerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ineptias:</hi> and Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> kept in ſome things to bring in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; and it had good effect: But ours being ſo well accommodated to Truth, Piety, and Devotion, there needs no other Alterations, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs better reaſons can be ſhewed, it being confeſſedly the beſt in the Chriſtian World. But, moreover, what good effect hath followed the ſix hundred Alterations in 1661? Who deſireth them at our hands? And their not deſiring them, argues they will not be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by them; but they expect ſuch things as they are not willing to ask, knowing they cannot be granted. His Objections from <hi>Tobit,</hi> and the old Tranſlation of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> have been already conſidered, and ſo hath that of the <hi>Athanaſian Creed:</hi> As to the Liturgy, therefore I commend Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to him, and the Diſſenters again, <hi>p.</hi> 76. of Concord: <hi>I conſtantly joyn with my Pariſh-Church in Liturgy and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and hope ſo to do while I live: I take the Common-Prayer to be bester incomparably, than many of the Sermons and Prayers that I hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His next charge, <hi>p.</hi> 15. is againſt <hi>Excommunication;</hi> which he ſays, <hi>Is ſometime denounced againſt the beſt of our People, right or wrong, for ſome Penny or Two-penny Cauſe.</hi> This is a groſs Scandal, for if any be ſued for ſmall matters, if it be due to their Miniſter, he is very unjuſt that will with-hold it; and the Excommunication is iſſued againſt ſuch, for the contempt of the Authority; which is practiſed in all other Churches, even in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as by an Order printed <hi>June</hi> 1571. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. <hi>Any ſmall Offence</hi> (ſay they) <hi>may juſtly deſerve Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, by reaſon of the contempt and diſobedience of the Offender.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He comes <hi>p.</hi> 16. to anſwer Objections: The firſt is, <hi>That altering any thing in this now Conſtituted Church, will be like the plucking a Beam but of a well built Houſe, which may endanger the whole Fabrick:</hi> To which he anſwers, <hi>If all had been of this mind, we could never have Reformed from Popery.</hi> This is very impertinent, for is there no greater reaſon to reform Falſe Doctrine, and Idolatrous Worſhip, than to change innocent and lawful Ceremonies in our well conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Church; there we are ſure we altered for the better, here we are not ſure but we may alter for the worſe.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>If we once begin to alter, where ſhall we ſtop?</hi> his Anſwer is, <hi>When any thing is propoſed to us, which is not fit to be done.</hi> This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is inſufficient upon his grounds, for he will not have the Church to judge what is fit, but to do what is unfitly demanded by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, whom he makes Judges what ought to be altered.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:101060:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. And he ſays, <hi>If we yield now, they will ſtill be craving, till they have taken all away:</hi> And there is a croſſing of his old Proverb by another: <hi>Give an Inch, and they will take an Ell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. <hi>That Alterations are required in ſome things, as was in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church. Anſw.</hi> We are not hound to obſerve all that the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church did, as their Love-Feaſts, and Deaconeſſes; which is the ſame, as if we were bound to revive the old <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Britiſh</hi> Laws: To which the Reply in brief is this: When old Laws or U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages are antiquated and laid aſide, by the common conſent of thoſe that inſtituted them, there remains nothing but our due Obedience to thoſe new Ones that are in force. I perceive now, this Champion's Arms grow feeble, and therefore he makes uſe of his Tongue, and thinks to ſupply the defect of Reaſon by railing; and his Bolt is quickly ſhot; but ſhot at randome, and hits No-body, for he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes his Mark: he aimed at the Prolocutor, by an <hi>Inuendo,</hi> that <hi>he was he who had been promoted in the Church, by him whom he ſtabs with a Motto: Nolumus leges Angliae mutare:</hi> Which was not ſpoken by the Prolocutor, but another perſon, who owed his Preferment to his own merit, and not another's favour; but whoever ſpake the words, they could not deſerve the name of a ſtab, unleſs the telling of a Truth be ſo; and that ancient ſaying may excuſe him: <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Socrates Amicus Plato magis amica veritas.</hi> But the other ſtab, that of the Church, is given her by the Author, who complements the Church, as, (<hi>Joab</hi> did <hi>Abner.</hi>) <hi>Art thou in health, my Mother?</hi> And the words are no ſooner out of his mouth, but the Sword is in her Bowels; which, as another <hi>Nero,</hi> he unnaturally rips up, though he had been long nouriſhed in them; nor doth he ſpare him whom he intended to vindicate, by changing the Motto into a <hi>Volumus leges Angliae mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare.</hi> And thus he inſults over his dying Mother, as if in his judgment her Caſe were deſperate, being reduced to the <hi>Ultimus Conatus Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> p. 18. That ſhe ſits down quietly, and languiſheth to death, rather then ſhe will make the leaſt effort to ſave herſelf: But (God be thanked) ſhe hath more dutiful Sons than this unnatural <hi>Brutus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſixth <hi>Object. p.</hi> 18. Our Author having ſo much miſt his mark, is ſo much in paſſion, that he is angry with, and as far as a plain contradiction will reach, ſtabs himſelf: The Objection is: <hi>We have no reaſon to make Alterations for the ſake of the Diſſenters, becauſe the fault of our Diviſions, is not from any Conſtitutions of ours, but from their obſtinacy and perverſeneſs, in unreaſonably diſſenting from them.</hi> To which his Anſwer is: <hi>I acknowledge all this to be true, that it is not the fault of the Church by any of its Conſtitutions, or Impoſitions, which are all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and good, but they Onely who refuſe to conform to them.</hi> Whereas in <hi>p.</hi> 3. he had affirmed, <hi>That thoſe excepted paſſages in the Liturgy,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101060:31"/>and thoſe Ceremonies in our Worſhip had given the whole Origine to thoſe prevailing Evils among us, and therefore thinks it neceſſary to lay aſide thoſe Penal Laws, and Church Cenſures, which have been inflicted with a Severity beyond what we can juſtifie; and this,</hi> he ſays, <hi>hath heightned our Diviſions, and increaſed the Miſchiefs which we endeavoured to remove.</hi> If ever I read a contradiction, this is one: What then is our Author's Opinion, but that our Penal Laws, and Church Cenſures muſt of <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity</hi> be laid aſide, and the Fathers of the Church be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to their diſobedient Children on their own terms; as if he had never read of thoſe terrible Judgments which were denounced againſt old <hi>Eli,</hi> for his fondneſs towards his profane Sons, who were Sons of <hi>Belial, That would endure no Yoke themſelves, and made the People to abhor the Offerings of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.17. <hi>And he reſtrained them not; but though they kicked at the Sacrifices and Offerings of the Lord, yet ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured his Sons more than God:</hi> Yet notwithſtanding this, he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the Church, as being too obſtinate, and obſtructing the Peace of the Church, and the Salvation of ſo many Souls; as if the Peace of the Church, and the Salvation of Souls, were not more probably to be promoted in the Church, than out of it; and the Peace of the Church more likely to be procured by a reſtraining of thoſe that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from it, rather than by complying with them, as he adviſeth. He tells us, indeed, <hi>That we are Phyſitians ſent to heal thoſe that are ſick and infirm; and when they refuſe a wholeſome Medicine, ought to think of ſomething agreeable to his humor and palate; but if the ſick Man become pieviſh,</hi> as he ſays, <hi>and nothing will pleaſe him, but what the Phyſitian knows will endanger his life, the Phyſitian ought not in compliance with his humor to hazard his life:</hi> A gentle reſtraint is more abſolutely neceſſary in ſuch caſes, than a fooliſh pity; nor can it be called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable ſeverity; for in ſuch caſes, <hi>Non perſequitur medicus aegrum ſed aeger Medicum:</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 7. <hi>If we make thoſe Alterations, how ſhall we anſwer the Papiſts, who will upbraid us with it?</hi> To this he anſwers: <hi>As well as we did in the firſt of Q.</hi> Elizabeth. <hi>Reply.</hi> Not ſo well; for ſhe altred ſome things that were ſuperſtitious, and yet kept up ſuch a decency as drew in many Papiſts to the Communion of the Church; as my Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> obſerved. 2. He ſays, <hi>We may alter now, as well as in</hi> 1662. And likely no better; for then, notwithſtanding the ſix hundred Alterations, the Diſſenters were Diſſenters ſtill. 3. <hi>We may anſwer the Papiſts,</hi> he ſays, <hi>by pleading their Alterations at the Council of</hi> Trent. Whereas that Council, were ſo far from complying with the then Diſſenters, that they made more ſevere Canons, and enjoyned them under their Anathemas; when we onely deſire to preſerve our own Conſtitutions, which our Author ſays, <hi>Are both Reaſonable and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:101060:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 8. <hi>We ſhall by theſe Alterations diſſatisfie our own People. Anſw.</hi> I believe there is more Noiſe than Truth or Reaſon in this Objection: <hi>There may be,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſome few ignorant or weak People that are zealouſly affected to theſe matters.</hi> But the Apoſtle accounted them to be the ſtronger and better inſtructed Chriſtians, who underſtood their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty as to things indifferent, and were ready to ſubmit to their Governours in ſuch things, for the Peace of the Church, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thoſe that were contentious againſt the uſe of them; the People ought not to preſcribe to the Church in ſuch things, but the Church to them: Nor is it a ſinful ſuppoſition in them that do obey, for they do not obey as to Divine Inſtitutions, but as to the Conſtitutions of the Church; and therefore we do not fear that they will deſert us, if we keep our ground. <hi>Thus far,</hi> ſaith our Author, <hi>I have ſhewn what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is upon us to conſent to the Alterations that will be propoſed in this preſent Convocation:</hi> A ſtrange kind of neceſſity, to conſent to what we never knew, be it right or wrong. A great Noiſe was made of conſenting to certain Homilies, that ſhould be ſet forth by Authority of Church and State; but here we muſt neceſſarily conſent to what will be propoſed by ſome few Men, who by this Man's Authority may impoſe what they will upon us; but of this he ſeems to be aſhamed, and therefore proceeds to another reaſon for this neceſſity, <hi>From the Promiſe made by the Biſhop to K.</hi> James; <hi>which if not performed, we muſt expect the general clamour of the People againſt us, as a baſe and falſe ſort of Men, who can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in times of Adverſity, and forget all when that is over; and ſo become the Reproach of every Man. Anſw.</hi> We are little obliged to this Author for his Miſrepreſentation of us, and of our Promiſes, which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional; if the Parliament and Convocation ſhould agree. And are the Biſhops in more proſperity now, than when they made thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? Are they in a condition to perform them now, if they were never ſo willing?</p>
            <p>This is the ſame, as if one man ſhould extort a promiſe from another <hi>in duris,</hi> and then ſo bind him up, that it ſhall be impoſſible for him to perform what he promiſed. The reproach of non-performance will lay on ſome other and not on him. Let the Biſhops be put <hi>in ſtatu quo,</hi> and then ſee what they will do; but this Objection our Author ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently Anſwers, when he ſays, <hi>There is no aſſurance that any one of the Diſſenters will come over to us (on our Conceſſions)</hi> and therefore it is in vain to proceed on this project; for as for his confidence that many would come in, he muſt know the minds of thoſe many better than they themſelves do, if he be aſſured of it; for the leaders of that multitude who are guided by them, have declared the contrary. And it being the intereſt of their Miniſters, who have a more plentiful income by their conventicles, as well as greater reſpects, and a larger power than they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101060:32"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hope for in a Church Benefice, will never be ſuch ſelf-denying persons, as to renounce all theſe Intereſts, and be brought into the Church to the loſs of them. <hi>But the people,</hi> ſaith our Author, <hi>will forſake them, and come into us if theſe Alterations be made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> On the contrary, its more probable that when we make Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations without their deſire, the Miniſters will tell them, we were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of our corrupt Worſhip, and have altered it in ſome leſſer, but have retained the greater matters to which they cannot yeild; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet many ſinful conditions in our conformity; and as the people are already in this belief, ſo they will from our voluntary Alterations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them in it, and gain more on their credulity: And from hence the Miniſters will not be left without excuſe, as long as they pretend any one ſinful term for a Communion with us is retained; and that pretence is like to hold as long as it is their intereſt to ſuggeſt it, and ſo long after all that we can grant, we ſhall ſtill be vexed with their Clamors.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>2ly,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>We ſhall by our Alterations give ſatisfaction to the Nation, who expects it, the main Body whereof,</hi> he ſays, <hi>ſtand indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected to them and us, and think the things ſtood upon to be but trifling matters.</hi> How the Nation will brook ſuch an accuſation, as if like <hi>Gallio,</hi> they cared not for the ſolemnity of Divine Worſhip, and were <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans,</hi> neither hot nor cold, for that which is Eſtabliſhed by Law, and hath been ſo long approved by their practice, let them ſhew and it were a ſhame if they ſhould not be as zealous for the Eſtabliſhed Worſhip, as the Diſſenters are for that which hath been ſo often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, though now it be Tolerated.</p>
            <p>But there is yet another neceſſity for Alterations, <hi>becauſe if we do it not, moſt certainly the Parliament will.</hi> This man talks as once <hi>Cromwel</hi> did, who having ſeized the Keys of the Parliament houſe, clapt them up, and ſaid, <hi>He had now the Parliament in his Pocket.</hi> Moſt certainly the preſent Parliament will not truckle under ſuch a degenerate Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and inſtead of thanks incur the <hi>Odium</hi> of the Nation, ſeeing this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Author ſays, <hi>If it come to their hands they may inſtead of Circumſtantials alter Eſſentials, and make a breach on Religion it ſelf to the undoing of all;</hi> and this I think is a <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> and this he fears will be done, <hi>not only in the caſe of Orders, but other Particulars, which he could inſtance in, of which the leaſt miſchief would be totally to extinguiſh all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations for the future, and reſolve the whole power of the Church into the Two Houſes of Parliament, and fix the reproach of the Papiſts on us, That our Religion is a Parliamentary Religion.</hi> For my part I ſhould fear the loſs of my Ears if I ſhould have thus ſlurd that Great Council, this would make what he would have the Church to be, <hi>Felo's de ſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Man (as other venomous Animals) keeps the ſting in his Tail, or the concluſion of his Libel, in Anſwer to a Third Objection, <hi>That ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:101060:32"/>neceſſary ſoever his Reaſons befor Alterations, yet it is time for it when ſo many of the Fathers of the Church, whom he acknowledgeth to be excellent and moſt Religious perſons, and other eminent Men of the Clergy, by their Suſpenſion, ſtand incapacitated to act in this matter; and if this be now done, when their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent cannot be had, they will renounce it all, and by ſticking to the preſent Form, create a new Schiſm in the Church; and this he hears is the reaſon much inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on to defeat the deſign and intent of this Convocation.</hi> But firſt I believe, (whatever may be the deſign of ſome Men) is not the intent of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; they may intend the better Eſtabliſhment of the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; they may intend the better Eſtabliſhment of the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, the Reformation of the Lives and Manners of ſome of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, by new Canons and Cenſures, to be provided againſt the Ignorance and Idleneſs of ſome, and the Irregularity and ſcandalous Behaviour of others, who either already are, or hereafter ſhall be admitted into the Miniſtry of the Church. But let us attend to his Anſwer to this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which we have <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>Is it poſſible to imagine,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that thoſe who have ſo eminently ſignaliz'd themſelves in defence of the Church, and been Confeſſors for it, ſhould turn their hands againſt it?</hi> No, <hi>It is affirmed before, that if they were admitted into the Convocation, they would agree to the intended Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and if any ſhould then ſeperate, they are ſuch as are moſt perverſely bent againſt Reaſon and Conſcience to do all the wickedneſs they can to gratifie a pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh humour; and therefore, he ſays, they that make this Objection, have a great deal to Anſwer for the injury which they do them by this ſlanderous and vile Imputation.</hi> For my part, I cannot be ſo confident, that thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Men would be ſo forward to make ſuch Alterations, as this Author ſays they would; and I ſee the Objectors are not without Reaſon on their ſide; for if they are ready to ſuffer the loſs of all that they have, rather than to offend their Conſciences by aſſenting to ſome Civil Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the State, (which what the Particulars be I cannot imngine, and therefore cannot judge of them) it may well be ſuppoſed, that they would be ſo tenderly conſcientious in reſpect to the Conſtitutions of the Church, as not to aſſent to any Alterations that concern the ſafety, honour, and beauty thereof, without important Reaſons. But what if they ſhould adhere to the old Form, and not yield to the intended Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations; why then our Author hath adviſed for their ruine; <hi>For their number,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is ſo ſmall, their Proſelytes will be ſo few, and the Reſentments of the State will be ſo heavy on them, that they will be immediately cruſhed, and fall to nothing.</hi> Which will be very hard meaſure, that ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Men ſhould not be allowed ſo much Liberty of Conſcience as <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> are, though they be known to be Men of ſound Doctrine, and of peaceable and harmleſs Lives: But it is yet their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, that ſuch as our Author is, are not made their Judges; for how we would deal with thoſe <hi>Scare-crows</hi> (as he terms them) <hi>which Knaves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lift up, but none but Fools can be frighted with;</hi> would probably be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> like the Knave than the Fool.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:101060:33"/>
            <p>And to conclude, he thinks his Argument of <hi>Abſolute Neceſſity</hi> ſo plain, that there can be no oppoſition, but from them that are afraid of their <hi>Church-power</hi> and <hi>Church-promotions,</hi> when they hear of <hi>Reformation:</hi> And in truth, that word was made an Engine of great miſchief in the former Age 1642, when the Church-men ſuffered more than they fear, now under the preſent Government, whatever this Author and his Abetters may deſign; for he ſeems to threaten us, <hi>That if we will not be contented with a moderate and juſt Reformation,</hi> he knows not but the Nation may take the matter into their own hands, and bring us to that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which, he ſays, we are ſo much afraid of, and deprive us of all: And then farewel our Church-promotions, and all their Revenues, which there will not want other Men to ſhare among themſelves, when ſuch a thorow Reformation ſhall be made as the <hi>Scots</hi> once procured, and have again deſigned: And therefore I dare not truſt the promiſe of this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſon, whoever he be, (for I fear he hath not been as faithful to his former ſolemn engagements as he ought) That upon our Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we ſhall find all the good ſucceſs that can be deſired; becauſe, as he ſays, <hi>there are appearances, at preſent, to the contrary;</hi> and they of ſuch an Aſpect, as will much abate the Credit which he expects ſhould be given to his promiſes; we had once very great promiſes from ſuch a ſort of Men, what a glorious King they would make of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and they did it; but it was by Martyrdom; and a godly Reformation was promiſed in the Church, but it proved a thorow Deſolation of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, Liturgy, and all that was Sacred; and as it was their fault then, ſo it will be ours now, if we by our too great credulity ſhall expoſe our ſelves to ruine a ſecond time, on a bare promſe of a faithleſs Man.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I have reflected on theſe two Killing Letters, and ſhall not concern my ſelf to enquire the Authors: They may be Papiſts, who by ſuch Arts ſeek to divide, that they may deſtroy us; nor can I perceive any other end in either Letter, but the carrying on a deſign of Self-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and Secular advantages, on the ruine of the Church. The firſt Author diſcovers his palpable Ignorance, the ſecond his viſible Malice: The one fights as <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> with Windmills diſturbing his Brain; The other acts as the <hi>Fur praedeſtinatus</hi> under a fatal neceſſity, by which he would excuſe all his Cheats and Robberies, as if he could not do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, being under the power of an Abſolute neceſſity; I ſhall leave it to the Convocation to conjecture who may be the Authors of theſe Letters, but that the One is a Miniſter of the Eſtabliſhed Church, and the Other, as he pretends, of the Preſent Convocation, I cannot be perſwaded, though he ſhould ſwear to it; becauſe by what is matter of fact, ſuch Men have acted contrary to their Oaths, and ſolemn Subſcriptions; and ſo I take my leave of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:101060:33"/>
            <head>An Hiſtorical ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>PRESENT CONVOCATION.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE CONVOCATION being Summon'd by the King's Writ, His Majeſty iſſued out another Commiſſion to thirty Divines, to prepare Matters to be Conſidered by the Convocation. The Commiſſion is as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>WHereas</hi> the particular Forms of Divine Worſhip, and the Rites and Ceremonies appointed to be us'd therein, being Things in their own Nature Indifferent and Alterable, and ſo acknowledged; It is but reaſonable, that, upon weighty and important Conſiderations, according to the various Exigencies of Times and Occaſions, ſuch Changes and Alterations ſhould be made therein, as to thoſe that are in Place and Authority ſhould from time to time ſeem ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Neceſſary or Expedient.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>And whereas</hi> the Book of Canons is fit to be Review'd, and made more ſutable to the State of the Church; and whereas there are Defects and Abuſes in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts and Juriſdictions, and particularly there is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Proviſion made for the Removing of Scandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and for the Reforming of Manners either in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or People: And whereas it is moſt fit that there ſhould be a ſtrict Method preſcribed for the Examination of ſuch Perſons as deſire to be admitted into Holy Orders, both as to their Learning and Manners.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>We therefore,</hi> out of Our Pious and Princely Care for the Good Order, and Ediſication, and Unity of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> committed to our Charge and Care; And for the Reconciling, as much as is poſſible, of all Differences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101060:34"/>Our Good Subjects, and to take away all Occaſions of the like for the future, have thought fit to Authorize and Empower You, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and any Nine of You, whereof Three to be Biſhops, to Meet from time to time, as often as ſhall be needful, and to Prepare ſuch Alterations of the Liturgy and Canons, and ſuch Propoſals for the Reformation of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Courts, and to Conſider of ſuch other Matters as in Your Judgments may moſt conduce to the Ends above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned.</q>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Commiſſioners, <hi>A. D. 1689.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tho. Lamplugh,</hi> Lord A. Biſh. of <hi>York.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Compton,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peter Mew,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Lloyd,</hi> Lord Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Sprat,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carſtile.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jonathan Trelauny,</hi> Ld. Biſhop of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humfrey Humfreys,</hi> Ld. Biſhop of <hi>Bangor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nicholas Stratford,</hi> Ld. Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edward Stillingfleet,</hi> late Dean of St. <hi>Pauls, Lond.</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Simon Patyick,</hi> late Dean of <hi>Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> D. D. late Dean of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> now Dean of St. <hi>Pauls, Lond.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rich. Meggot,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Sharp,</hi> D. D. late Dean of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> now Dean of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rich. Kidder,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Peterborough</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Aldridge,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Chriſt-Church, Oxford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Will. Jane,</hi> D. D. <hi>Regius</hi> Profeſſor of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity in the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Hall,</hi> D. D. <hi>Margaret</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in the Univerſity of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Joſeph Beaumont,</hi> D. D. <hi>Regius</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Divinity in the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Mountague,</hi> D. D. and Mr. of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Colledge</hi> in the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Goodman,</hi> D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Will Beveradge,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Colobeſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Battely,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Alſton,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Teniſon,</hi> D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Scot,</hi> D. D. Prebendary of St. <hi>Pauls, London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edward Fowler,</hi> D. D. Prebendary of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Grove,</hi> D. D. Prebendary of St. <hi>Pauls, London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Williams,</hi> D. D. Prebendary of St. <hi>Pauls, London.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>What things were debated by them, are not yet commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the Convocation; only it is known, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Prolocutor, and ſome other Learned and Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, deſerted them, as diſliking ſeveral Propoſals, which the reſt inſiſted on.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:101060:34"/>
               <head>The Particular Acts and Adjournments OF THE <hi>CONVOCATION,</hi> From <hi>December</hi> the 4th, 1689.</head>
               <p>THE Litany was read by a Biſhop, for ſome days in Latine, there being only this Supplication added, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Prayers for the Biſhops:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it may pleaſe Thee to inſpire with Thy Holy Spirit this Convocation, and to preſide over it, to lead us into all Truth, which is according to Godlineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At other times when there was no Sermon, this Prayer for the Parliament was conſtantly uſed:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOst Gracious God who dost Rule all Men, and Govern all Things, be graciouſly preſent, we beſeech Thee, with the three Eſtates of the Kingdom in Parliament aſſembled, under the Government of our most Gracious Princes</hi> William <hi>and</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; <hi>Aſſist them with the Spirit of Counſel and Peace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be preſerved in one Mind and Accord, and alſo may be inſpired with the Love of Thee, and Study the Publick Welfare; that whatſoever Laws, by their joynt Suffrages ſhall be obtain'd, being eſtabliſhed by our Lord and Lady, the King and Queen, may eſtabliſh Righteouſneſs and Peace to us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them to our Roſterities for ever, to the encreaſe of all Vertue, and the Eternal Glory of Thy Name, by and for Jeſus Christ our Lord and Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then follow'd theſe Five Collects: I. The Collect on St. <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi>'s Day, <hi>O Almighty God, who hast built thy Church upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Collect for <hi>Good-Friday, Almighty and Everlaſting God, by whoſe Spirit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:101060:35"/>
               <p n="3">III. Collect, <hi>Almighty God who by thy Son Jeſus Christ didst give to the Holy Apoſtles many excellent Gifts, and commandst them Earneſtly to feed thy Flock, Make, we beſeech thee, all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Paſtors diligently to preach thy Holy Word; and the People obediently to follow the ſame, that they may receive the Crown of Everlaſting Glory, thro' Jeſus Christ our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. The Collect on the Fifth <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Trinity, Grant we beſeech Thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Collect, <hi>O Lord God the Father of Lights, and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all Wiſdom, we thy humble and unworthy Servants, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating ourſelves at thy Footſtool, beſeech thee, that we who are here met together in thy Name, under the Government of our most Gracious King</hi> WILLIAM <hi>and Queen</hi> MARY, <hi>being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by thy heavenly Grace, may ſo ſearch out, meditate, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and diſcern all things which may promote thy Honour and Glory, and the Good of thy Church, that thy Spirit, which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore did preſide over the Council of the Apoſtles, may alſo preſide over this our Council, and lead us into all that Truth which is according to Godlineſs; that we who have worthily and ſeriouſly, utterly renounced the Errours of our holy Reformation, the Corruptions and Superſtitions, together with the Papal Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny which heretofore did here abound, may all of us firmly: and conſtantly hold the Apoſtolick and truly Catholick Faith, and without fear, may duly ſerve thee with a pure Worſhip, through Jeſus Christ our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Then follows the Prayer of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome: Almighty God who hast given us Grace at this time,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then the Members of the Convocation were called over:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Alphabetical Catalogue of all the Names of the Members of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper and Lower Houſe of this preſent CONVOCATION.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William,</hi> Ld. Bp. of St. <hi>Aſaph.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Geor. Bright,</hi> D. D. Dean of St. <hi>Aſaph.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Samuel Davies,</hi> L. D. Proctor for the Chapter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William,</hi> Lord Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> Arch-Deacon of St. <hi>Aſaph.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Griffin Lloyd,</hi> B. D. <hi>John Edwards,</hi> A. M. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ralph Bathurſt,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rich. Busby,</hi> D. D. Proct. for the Chapter.</item>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:101060:35"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edwin Sandys,</hi> A. M. Archd of <hi>Wells. Bath. Taunton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edw. Waple,</hi> B. D. Archd of <hi>Wells. Bath. Taunton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Clement,</hi> A. M. <hi>Giles Pooley,</hi> A. M. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Humphrey,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Bangor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Jones,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Bangor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rob. Foulks,</hi> A M. Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Humphrey,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Bangor,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Bangor</hi> and <hi>Angleſey.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fran. Lloyd,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Merioneth.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robert Wynne,</hi> A. M. <hi>John Williams,</hi> A. M. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gilbert,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Levett,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Steph. Creſpion,</hi> A. M. Proct. for the Chap.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Feilding,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Dorſet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Roger Mander,</hi> D. D. <hi>Rich. Roderick,</hi> B. D. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Canterbury.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> D. D. then Dean of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> now Dean of St. <hi>Paul's Lond.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>— Proctor for the Chapter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Joh. Batteley,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>George Thorpe,</hi> D. D. <hi>John Cooke,</hi> A. M. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Simon,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Francis Hawkins,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Zach. Cradock,</hi> D. D. Proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Joſias Pleydell,</hi> A. M. Archdeacon of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Joſeph Sayer,</hi> B. D. Archd. of <hi>Lewes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Conyers Richardſon,</hi> A. M. <hi>David Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> D. D. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas,</hi> Ld. Bp. of St. <hi>Davids.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Ellis,</hi> D. D. <hi>Praecentor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Spencer Lucy</hi> A M. Proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tim. Halton,</hi> D. D. Archd. of St. <hi>Davids.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Geo. Owen,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Carmarthen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Stainoe,</hi> B. D. Archd. of <hi>Brecknock.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Joh. Williams,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Cardigan,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Sandys,</hi> A. M. <hi>William Powell</hi> A. M. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Ely.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Spencer,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Ely.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Moore,</hi> D. D. proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Saywell,</hi> D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>Ely.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Samuel Blith,</hi> D. D. <hi>Nicholas Gouge,</hi> A. M. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Jonathan,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rich. Anneſley,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Exon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Geo. Hooper,</hi> D. D. proct. for the Chapter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edward Lake,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edw. Drew,</hi> A M. Archd. of <hi>Cornwall.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fra. Fulwood,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Totnes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Read,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Barum.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John James,</hi> D. D. <hi>Tho. Long,</hi> Senior, B. D. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Gloceſter.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Jane,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Prolocutor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rich Duke,</hi> A. M. proctor for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Hide,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Abraham Gregory,</hi> D. D. <hi>Rich. Parſons,</hi> L. D. Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Herbert,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>George Benſon, D. D.</hi> Dean of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Rogers, D. D.</hi> proctor for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sam. Benſon,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Adam Ottley,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Salop.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Johnſon, D. D. Rich. Bulkley,</hi> A. M. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Landaffe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry Bull, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Landaffe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Jonathan Edwards,</hi> proctor for the Chapter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Frampton,</hi> A. M.—<hi>Jenkins,</hi> A. M. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Coventry.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lancelot Addiſon, D. D.</hi> Dean of <hi>Lich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Willes, D. D.</hi> proctor for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lancelot Addiſon, D. D.</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Coventry.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fran. Aſhenhurſt,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Darby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fran. Aſhenhurſt,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Stafford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fran. Aſhenhurſt,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Salop.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:101060:36"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Barnabas Poole,</hi> A. M. <hi>Jo. Kimberley,</hi> A. M. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas,</hi> Lord Bp. of <hi>Lincoin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Daniel Brevint, D. D.</hi> Dean of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Inet,</hi> A. M. <hi>Samuel Fuller, D. D.</hi> proctors for the Chapter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Oldys,</hi> L. B. Archd. of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Hutton,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Stow.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Byrom Eaton, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Hamond, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Bucks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Gery, L. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Huntington.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Skelton,</hi> A. M. Archd. of <hi>Bedford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>James Gardiner, D. D. Robert Edwards, B. D.</hi> Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>London,</hi> Preſ.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>J. Tillotſon, D. D.</hi> now D. of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Stanley, D. D.</hi> Proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Teniſon, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Goodman, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Charles Alſton, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Beveridge, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Cole,</hi> A. M. Archd. of St. <hi>Albans.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gregory Haſcard, D. D. Robert Grove, D. D.</hi> Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Norwich.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Sharpe, D. D.</hi> then Dean of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> now Dean of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nath. Hodges,</hi> A. M. Proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Conant, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edw. Reynolds, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Spencer, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Sudbury.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hum. Prideaux, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Connald,</hi> A. M. <hi>John Eachard, D. D.</hi> Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Oxford.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hen. Aldrich, D. D.</hi> D. of <hi>Chriſt-Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hen. Smith, D. D.</hi> Proct. for the Chapter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Timothy Halton, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Oxon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Mill, D. D. Henry Maurice, D. D.</hi> Proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Peterborough</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rich. Kidder, D. D.</hi> Dean of <hi>Peterbour.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Patrick,</hi> A. M. Proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Woolſey, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Northampt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Matthew Hutton, B. D. Nath: Whalley,</hi> A. M. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>llock, D. D.</hi> Dean of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fran. Brevall, D. D.</hi> proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Plume, D. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richard Holden,</hi> A. M. <hi>Joſeph Yates,</hi> A. M. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gilbert,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Price, D. D.</hi> Dean of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robert Woodward, L. D.</hi> proctor for the Chapter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Richards, B. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Lambert,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Berks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Ward, L. D.</hi> Archd. of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Younger,</hi> D. D. <hi>Thomas Wyat,</hi> D. D. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Weſtminſter.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> Dean of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edw. Pelling,</hi> D. D. proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rich. Busby,</hi> D. D. Archd. of <hi>Weſtminſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Peter,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rich. Meggott,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Winton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will: Hawkins,</hi> D. D. proct. for the Chapt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Clutterbuck,</hi> D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Sayer,</hi> D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>Surrey.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Harriſon,</hi> D. D. <hi>George Hooper,</hi> D. D. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>Windſor. <hi>No Return.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Wolverhampton. <hi>No Return.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward,</hi> Ld. Bp. of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Hicks,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>R. Battle,</hi> A. M. proct. for the Chapter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Fleetwood,</hi> A. M. Archdeacon of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Jephcott,</hi> D. D. <hi>Tho. Hodge,</hi> A. M. proctors for the Clergy.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And after this, the Prolocutor was choſen: The Perſons named, were Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and Dr. <hi>Jane,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:101060:36"/>the King's Profeſſor in <hi>Oxford;</hi> Dr. <hi>Jane</hi> had the Majority of Voices; yet great endeavours were uſed to prefer the Dean, whoſe Party having argued much for it, but ſaw themſelves overcome, did at laſt yeild to the Election of Dr. <hi>Jane,</hi> the Votes for him being double to the others.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing that was done in the Convocation, after the chuſing the Prolocutor, was, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 4th, when the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the King was read, there being preſent twelve Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; the Commiſſion was as follows:</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="commission">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WIlliam</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King and Queen of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defenders of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c. <hi>To all to whom theſe Preſents ſhall come, Greeting; Whereas,</hi>
                        </hi> in and by one Act of Parliament made at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the 25th Year of the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, Reciting, That whereas the King's Humble and Obedient Subjects, the Clergy of this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> had not only acknowledged according to the Truth, that the Convocation of the ſame Clergy, were always, had been, and ought to be Aſſembled only by the King's Writ, but alſo ſubmitting themſelves to the King's Majeſty, had promiſed in <hi>Verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> that they would never from thenceforth preſume to Attempt, Alledge, Claim, or put in Ure, or Enact, Promulge, or Execute any new Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Conſtitutions, Ordinances Provincial or others, or by whatſoever other Name they ſhould be called in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, unleſs the ſaid King's moſt Royal Aſſent and Licenſe might to them be had, to Make, Promulge and Execute the ſame; and that the ſaid King did give his Royal Aſſent and Authority in that behalf.</p>
                     <p>It was therefore Enacted by the Authority of the ſaid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, according to the ſaid Submiſſion and Petition of the ſaid Clergy, among other things, That they, nor any of them from thenceforth ſhould Enact, Promulge or Execute any ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions or Ordinances Provincial,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101060:37"/>by whatſoever Name they might be called in their Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in time coming, which always ſhould be Aſſembled by Authority of the King's Writ, unleſs the ſame Clergy might have the King's moſt Royal Aſſent and Licenſe, to Make, Promulge and Execute ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions and Ordinances, Provincial or Synodal, upon Pain of every one of the ſaid Clergy doing contrary to the ſaid Act, and being thereof Convict, to ſuffer Impriſonment, and make Fines at the King's Will.</p>
                     <p>And further, by the ſaid Act it is Provided, That no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Conſtitutions or Ordinances ſhould be Made, or put in Execution within this Realm, by Authority of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations of the Clergy, which ſhould be contrariant or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the King's Prerogative Royal, or the Cuſtoms, Laws or Statutes of this Realm, any thing contained in the ſaid Act to the contrary thereof notwithſtanding.</p>
                     <p>And laſtly, It is alſo Provided by the ſaid Act, That ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions, Ordinances and Synodals Provincial, which then were already made, and which then were not contrariant or repugnant to the Laws, Statutes and Cuſtoms of this Realm, nor to the Damage or Hurt of the King's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Royal; ſhould then ſtill be Uſed and Executed as they were before the making of the ſaid Act, until ſuch time as they ſhould be Viewed, Searched, or otherwiſe Ordered and Determin'd by the Perſons mentioned in the ſaid Act, or the moſt part of them, according to the Tenor, Form and Effect of the ſaid Act, as by the ſaid Act, among divers other things more fully and at large, it doth and may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
                     <p>And whereas the particular Forms of Divine Worſhip, and Rites and Ceremonies appointed to be uſed therein, being Things of their own Nature Indifferent and Alterable, and ſo acknowledged, it is but reaſonable, that upon weighty and important Conſiderations, according to the various Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igency of Times and Occaſions; ſuch Changes and Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:101060:37"/>ſhould be made therein, as to thoſe that are in Place and Authority, ſhould from time to time, ſeem either neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary or expedient.</p>
                     <p>And whereas the Book of Canons is fit to be Reviewed, and made more ſuitable to the State of the Church: And whereas there are divers Defects and Abuſes in the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Courts and Juriſdictions; and particularly there is not ſufficient Proviſion made for the removing of Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Miniſters, and for the Reformation of Manners either in Miniſters or People; And whereas it is moſt fit, that there ſhould be a ſtrict Method preſcribed for the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Perſons as deſire to be admitted into Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, both as to their Learning and Manners: Know ye, That We, for divers urgent and weighty Cauſes and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, Us thereunto moving, of Our eſpecial Grace, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Knowledge, and meer Motion, have by Vertue of Our Prerogative Royal, and Supream Authority in Cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, Given and Granted, and by theſe Preſents do give and grant, full, free and lawful Liberty, Licenſe, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority, into the Right Reverend Father in GOD, <hi>Henry</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> Preſident of this Preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, for the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (upon the Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Lord Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) during this preſent Parliament now Aſſembled; and in his Abſence, to ſuch other Biſhops as ſhall be appointed Preſident thereof, and to the reſt of the Biſhops of the ſame Province, and to all Deans of Cathedral Churches, Arch-Deacons, Chapters and Colledges, and the whole Clergy of every ſeveral Dioceſs, within the ſaid Province; That they the ſaid Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> or other Preſident of the ſaid Convocation, and the reſt of the Biſhops, and other the ſaid Clergy of this preſent Convocation within the ſaid Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or the greateſt number of them, whereof the Preſident of the ſaid Convocation to be always one, ſhall and may from time to time, during this preſent Parliament, Confer, Treat, Debate,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101060:38"/>Conſider, Conſult, and Agree of and upon ſuch Points, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Cauſes and Things, as We from time to time ſhall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or cauſe to be propoſed by the ſaid Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> or other Preſident of the ſaid Convocation, comer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Alterations and Amendments of the Liturgy and Canons, and Orders, Ordinances and Conſtitutions for the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Eccleſiaſtical Courts, for the Removing of Scandalous Miniſters, for the Reformation of Manners either in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or People, and for the Examination of ſuch Perſons as deſire to be admitted into Holy Orders, and all ſuch other Points, Cauſes and Matters as We ſhall think Neceſſary and Expedient, for advancing the Honour and Service of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD, the Good and Quiet of the Church, and the better Government thereof.</p>
                     <p>And we do alſo by theſe Preſents, Give and Grant unto the ſaid Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> or other Preſident of the ſaid Covocation, and to the reſt of the Biſhops of the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and unto all Deans of Cathedral Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Arch-Deacons, Chapters and Colledges, and the whole Clergy of every ſeveral Dioceſs within the ſaid Province, full, free and lawful Liberty, Licenſe, Power and Authority, That they the ſaid Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> or other Preſident of the ſaid Convocation, and the reſt of the ſaid Biſhops, and other the Clergy of the ſame Province, or the greateſt Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that ſhall be preſent in Perſon, or by their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies, ſhall and may from time to time, draw into Forms, Rules, Orders, Ordinances, Conſtitutions and Canons, ſuch Matters as to them ſhall ſeem Neceſſary and Expedient for the Purpoſes abovementioned; and the ſame ſet down in Writing, from time to time, to Exhibit and Deliver, or cauſe to be Exhibited and Delivered unto us, to the end that We, as Occaſion ſhall require, may thereupon have the Advice of Our Parliament: And that ſuch, and ſo many of the ſaid Canons, Orders, Ordinances, Conſtitutions, Matters, Cauſes and Things as ſhall be thought Requiſite and Convenient by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101060:38"/>Our ſaid Parliament, may be preſented to Us in due Form, for Our Royal Aſſent, if upon Mature Conſideration thereof, We ſhall think fit to Enact the ſame. <hi>In Witneſs whereof,</hi> We have cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patent; Witneſs Ourſelves at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the 30th Day of <hi>November,</hi> in the Firſt Year of Our Reign,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Per Breve de privato Sigello,</hi> BURKER. Vera Copia, <hi>J. C. N. P.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>His Majeſty's Gracious Meſſage to the Convocation, ſent by the Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> as followeth:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>WILLIAM R.</signed>
                     </opener>
                     <p>HIs Majeſty has Summon'd this Convocation, not only becauſe 'tis uſual upon holding of a Parliament, but out of a Pious Zeal to do every thing that may tend to the beſt Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is ſo eminent a Part of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and is certainly the beſt ſuited to the Conſtitution of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and therefore does moſt ſignally deſerve, and ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have both His Favour and Protection; and he doubts not, but that you will aſſiſt Him in promoting the Welfare of it, ſo that no Prejudices, with which ſome Men may have laboured to poſſeſs you, ſhall diſappoint His good Intentions, or deprive the Church of any Benefit from your Conſultations. His Majeſty therefore expects, that the Things that ſhall be propoſed, ſhall be calmly and impartially Conſidered by you, and aſſures you, that he will offer nothing to you but what ſhall be for the Honour, Peace, and Advantage both of the Proteſtant Religion in general, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Biſhops ADDRESS:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WE Your Majeſty's most Dutiful Subjects, the Biſhops and Clergy of the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in Convocation aſſembled, having received Your Majeſty's Gracious Meſſage, together with a Commiſſion from Your Majeſty, by the Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> hold ourſelves bound in Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Duty, to return our most Humble Thanks and Acknowledgements of the Grace and Goodneſs expreſſed in Your Majeſty's Meſſage, and the Zeal You ſhew in it for the Proteſtant Religion in general, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> in particular, and of the Trust and Confidence repoſed in us by this Commiſſion: We look on theſe Marks of Your Majeſty's Care and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as the Continuance of the great Deliverance Almighty God wrought
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101060:39"/>for us by Your Means, in making You the Bleſſed Inſtrument of Preſerving us from falling under the Cruelty of Popiſh Tyranny; for which as we have often Thanked Almighty God, ſo we cannot forget that high Obligation and Duty which we owe to Your Majeſty; and on theſe new Aſſurances of Your Protection and Favour to our Church, we beg leave to renew the Aſſurance of our conſtant Fidelity and Obedience to Your Majeſty, Whom we Pray GOD to continue Long, and Happily to Reign over us.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Addreſs was not approved of by the Lower Houſe, who thought they had the Priviledge (wanting the Books of Preſidents) to preſent one of their own drawing; but that not being admitted, it was voted by the Lower Houſe, to make ſome Amendments; which were not agreed on, till after a Conference with the Biſhops, the Lower Houſe inſiſting, that they would confine themſelves to the King's Declaration, and to what concerned eſpecially the Church of <hi>England;</hi> whereupon a Conference was deſired, and a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee appointed to attend the Lords: The Conference was managed chiefly between the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and the Prolocutor; the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop urged, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> was not diſtinguiſhed from other Proteſtant Churches, but by its Hierarchy and Revenues, and that it was an equivocal Expreſſion; for if Popery ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, it would be called the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſtill. To which the Prolocutor anſwered, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> was diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by its Doctrine, as it ſtands in the Articles, Liturgy, and Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as well as by its Hierarchy, and that the Term of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches was much more Equivocal, becauſe <hi>Socinians, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> aſſumed that Title. After this, we heard no more Reply, but a Committee of the Convocation, in the Lower Houſe, having drawn up another Form, it was conſented to. And Thanks were given to the Prolocutor, for managing the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               <p>And the Addreſs, as agreed on, to be Preſented, was as followeth:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WE Your Majeſty's most Loyal and most Dutiful Subjects, the Biſhops and Clergy of the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in Convocation Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, having received a most Gracious Meſſage from Your Majeſty, by the Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> hold ourſelves bound in Duty and Gratitude, to return our most Humble Acknowledgments for the ſame; and for the Pious Zeal and Care Your Majeſty is pleaſed to expreſs therein for the Honour, Peace, Advantage, and Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101060:39"/>we doubt not, the Interest of the Proteſtant Religion in all other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches, which is dear to us, will be the better ſecured under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Your Majeſt's Government and Protection. And we crave leave to aſſure Your Majeſty, That in purſuance of that Trust and Confidence You repoſe in us, we will conſider whatſoever ſhall be offered to us from Your Majeſty, without Prejudice, and with all Calmneſs and Impartiality: And that we will conſtantly Pay the Fidelity and Allegiance, which we have all Sworn to Your Majeſty and the Queen; Whom we pray GOD to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Long, and Happily to Reign over us.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Addreſs was preſented on <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 12th of <hi>December,</hi> in the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting-Chamber.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty's moſt Gracious Anſwer to the Biſhops Addreſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Take this Addreſs very kindly from the Convocation: You may depend upon it, that all I have promiſed, and all that I can do for the Service of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I will do: And I give you this new Aſſurance, that I will improve all Occaſions and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for its Service.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <list>
                  <item>I. In the Adjournments it was firſt debated, What Proxies each Man might have, from thoſe that were abſent; and it was agreed, that one Man might have four.</item>
                  <item>II. Whether thoſe Biſhops that had Arch-Deaconries annexed to their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks, might grant Proxies to any Member of the Lower Houſe of Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to Vote for them.</item>
                  <item>III. Whether ſuch Proctors for the Clergy, as had not appeared, might grant their Proxies; Which was reſolved in the Affirmative, Preſidents being found for the ſame.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Then it was complained, that the Convocation wanted the Books of Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents belonging to the Convocation; and it being ſaid, that the Biſhop of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaph,</hi> and Dean <hi>Tillotſon</hi> had ſuch Books, they were deſired to bring them in; which was done, and a Committee appointed to inſpect them, and report what Preſidents could be found, that might concern the Convocation, which is yet under Examination. It was propoſed, that a Committee might be continued during the Adjournment, to prepare things againſt their Meeting; but this was denied. Complaint was made of ſome dangerous Books printed contrary to the Canons, as that againſt the Creed of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> which was ſent to the Biſhops to be Cenſured by them. A Reverend Perſon made a Speech on the behalf of the Biſhops under Suſpenſion, that ſomething might be done to qualifie them to ſit in Convocation, but ſo as the Convocation might not incur any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; which being not in their Cognizance, it was waved, and left to farther Conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:101060:40"/>
               <head>The MINUTE PARTICULARS Obſerv'd in the <hi>Proceedings of the CONVOCATION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>4 <hi>December,</hi> 1689.</p>
               <p>PRayers being ended, the King's Commiſſion brought in with a Meſſage by the Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> both which being read, the Biſhops went to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi>-Chamber, from whence they ſent a Copy of the King's Meſſage, with the Form of an Addreſs, to which they deſir'd the Concurrence of this Houſe.</p>
               <p>Dean of <hi>Windſor,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, <hi>Exon,</hi> deſired by this Houſe, to attend the Lords, to know whether they were all conſenting to the ſaid Addreſs, and likewiſe to pray a Copy of the ſaid Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>They Reported from the Lords, That they were conſenting to the ſaid Addreſs, and order'd to be ſent down to this Houſe, and deſir'd their Concurrence; and that they would order a Copy of the Commiſſion. Then a Queſtion aroſe, Whether this Houſe ſhould concur with the Form recommended by the Biſhops, or Addreſs the King in their own Form?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolv'd by this Houſe,</hi> To return Thanks to the King in a Form of their own.</p>
               <p>Dean of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> Dean of <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> deſir'd to attend the Lords with their Reſolution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That nothing of any moment be agreed upon, or paſs into an Act, till the old Books of former Convocations are brought in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Pleydell</hi>'s Proxy be withdrawn.</p>
               <p>The Biſhops deſiring a Conference,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That the Dean of <hi>Christ-Church, Chicheſter, Litchfield, Briſtol, St. Paul's, Peterborough,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>, <hi>Hooper, Maurice, Willis,</hi> be deſired to attend the Lords, to acquaint them, that the Houſe conſents to a Conference, and have appointed Managers, but deſire a longer time to prepare Inſtructions for them.</p>
               <p>The Lords appointed <hi>Friday</hi> Morning, nine of the Clock, to be attended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Conference.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That the ſame Perſons, together with the Prolocutor, Deans of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, Exon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Battely,</hi> and Archd. <hi>Feilding,</hi> be appointed a Committee, to draw up Inſtructions, to Morrow at nine of the Clock.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adjourn'd to the</hi> 6th.</p>
               <p>6 <hi>Decemb.</hi> Prayers ended, the old Books, and the Copy of the Commiſſion brought in. The Committee brought in an Addreſs, with Alterations, with the Reaſons why they cannot concur with the Biſhops in their Form, in theſe words, <hi>We are deſirous to confine our Addreſs to his Majeſty's most Gracious Meſſage, and to thoſe things only therein, which concern the Church of</hi> England; which Reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing approved of, and agreed to by this Houſe, it was carried up to the Lords by the ſaid Committee; who Reported from their Lordſhips, That what Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons this Houſe makes in their Lordſhips Addreſs, ought to be ſpecified in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Lines thereof in particular Exceptions.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:101060:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That the Form of Amendments ſent down by the Lords, be referred to the ſame Committee, to meet to Morrow at eight of the Clock, at Dr. <hi>Busby</hi>'s Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſaving this Houſe's right of Proceedings, in their own way, in this and the like caſes, where there is no Precedent to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That the Houſe adhere to the Reaſon of their Amendments, which was offered to the Lords.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>, <hi>Teniſon, Fuller, Beveredge, Hamond, Halton, Thorpe, Parſons, Gregory, Grove, Saywell, Alſton, Mander, Woodward, Goodman, Busby, Younger, Moore, Stanley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Kimberley, Richardſon, Ottley, Buckley,</hi> and <hi>Skelton,</hi> be appointed a Committee, to inſpect the old Books belonging to the Convocation, and where they find them defective, to offer new Orders, for the Approbation of this Houſe: Eleven whereof to be a <hi>Quorum,</hi> and to meet at three this Afternoon at Dr. <hi>Teni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Library.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adjourn'd till to Morrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7 <hi>Decemb.</hi> Prayers ended, the Committee return'd the Biſhops Form of Addreſs Alter'd and Amended according to the order of the Houſe Yeſterday, which being approv'd of by this Houſe, they were deſir'd to carry it up to the Lords.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adj till</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>9 <hi>Decemb.</hi> Prayers ended, the Committee return'd the Biſhops Form of Addreſs, Alter'd according to the order of the Houſe on <hi>Friday,</hi> which being approved of, they were again to carry it up to the Lords, (being prevented by the Adjournment on <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> from attending their Lordſhips with it) who brought down three Reaſons from their Lordſhips, why the expreſs mention of the Proteſtant Religion, ſhould be inſerted in the Addreſs, which are as follow: 1. <hi>Becauſe it is the known denomination of the common Doctrine of the Weſtern part of Chriſtendom, in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Errors and Corruptions of the Church of</hi> Rome. 2. <hi>Becauſe the leaving out this, may have ill conſequences, and be liable to ſtrange conſtructions, both at home and abroad, among Proteſtants as well as Papiſts.</hi> 3. <hi>Becauſe it agrees with the general Reaſon offer'd by the Clergy for their Amendments, ſince this is expreſly mentioned in the King's Meſſage; and in this the Church of</hi> England <hi>being ſo much concerned, the Biſhops think it ought ſtill to ſtand in the Addreſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then a Queſtion aroſe, Whether the conſideration of theſe Reaſons ſhould be referred to a Committee, or debated in a full Houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolv'd,</hi> That it be debated.</p>
               <p>After the debate, the Houſe agreed, that after theſe words in the Addreſs, <hi>(viz.) The Eſtabliſhment of the Church of</hi> England) it be immediately added, <hi>Whereby we doubt not the Interest of all the Proteſtant Churches, which is dear to us, will under the influence of Your Majeſty's Government, be the better ſecured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> The Lords deſiring a Committee from this Houſe, to inſpect the old Books, That D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>, <hi>Teniſon, Mauder, Woodward, Halton, Moore, Gregory,</hi> Mr. <hi>Skelton</hi> and <hi>Ottley,</hi> be appointed a Committee, to attend the Lords this Afternoon, at five a Clock, to inſpect the old Books.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adjourn'd till to Morrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>10 <hi>Decemb.</hi> Prayers ended, a Meſſage came down from the Lords, for the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agers to attend their Lordſhips; who Reported from their Lordſhips, That they deſire the reaſon of this Houſe, why inſtead of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> they inſert <hi>Proteſtant Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That the ſame Managers be appointed to draw up their Reaſons imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately; who return'd their Reaſon in theſe words: <hi>We being the Repreſentative <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f a form'd eſtabliſht Church, do not think fit to mention the word Religion, any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101060:41"/>then it is the Religion of ſome form'd eſtabliſht Church.</hi> Which Reaſon being approv'd, it was carried up to the Lords.</p>
               <p>The Lords return'd the Amendments with ſome Alterations, in theſe words: <hi>After the words</hi> (Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) <hi>add, Whereby we doubt not, the Interest of the Proteſtant Religion, in this and all other Proteſtant Churches, which is dear to us, will be the better ſecured under your Majeſty's Government and Protection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd by the Houſe,</hi> That the words, <hi>this and,</hi> be omitted.</p>
               <p>The Prolocutor, at the Requeſt of the Houſe, gave an Account of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the Lords.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Order'd,</hi> That the Thanks of the Houſe be given to the Prolocutor, for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aging the Conference with the Lords.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adjourn'd till to Morrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>11 <hi>Decemb.</hi> Prayers ended, the Prolocutor Reported from the Lords, That they had agreed to all the Amendments with this Houſe; and that they would give this Houſe an account this Morning, when it would be a fit time to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Majeſty with the ſaid Addreſs.</p>
               <p>Then the Houſe deſir'd the Prolocutor to attend the Lords, and humbly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to their Lordſhips, That there are ſeveral Books of very dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Chriſtian Religion, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> particularly; Notes upon <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Creed, and two Letters relating to the preſent Convocation, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come abroad; and to deſire their Lordſhips Advice, in what way, and how far, ſafely, without incurring the Penalty of the Statute 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. the Convocation may proceed, in the preventing the Publiſhing the like Scandalous Books for the future, and inflicting the Cenſure of the Church, according to the Canons provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that behalf, upon the Authors of them.</p>
               <p>Then the Prolocutor acquainted the Houſe, That their Lordſhips received the Meſſage very kindly, and promiſed to take it into conſideration; And alſo, that this Houſe is deſired to attend their Lordſhips at the Banquetting-Houſe to Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row at three of the Clock, to preſent the ſaid Addreſs to his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adj. to Friday.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>13 <hi>Decemb.</hi> Prayer ended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adjourn'd till to Morrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prayers ended, a Copy of the King's Anſwer to the Addreſs, ſent down from the Lords.</p>
               <p>The Prolocutor acquainted the Houſe, That the Preſident had declared his ſence of the ill conſequence of thoſe Books that were ſent up from this Houſe, to their Lordſhips; and that upon inquiry, he could not receive any ſatisfaction, how far the Convocation might proceed in that affair, but he would as far as lay in him, take further order about it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agreed by this Houſe,</hi> That the Prolocutor return Thanks to the Preſident for the care he hath taken about our Propoſal concerning the Books, and to deſire his Lordſhip to proceed further in it.</p>
               <p>Then it was propoſed by the Lords, to appoint a Committee of both Houſes to ſit during the Receſs.</p>
               <p>After ſome debate,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That this Houſe does not conſent to appoint any Committee during the ſaid Receſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adjourn'd to the</hi> 24th <hi>of</hi> January.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
